<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A justification of the directors of the Netherlands East Indie Company As it was delivered over unto the high and mightly lords the States General of the United Provinces, the 22th of July, 1686. Upon the subject and complaint of Mr. Skelton, Envoye Extraordinary from the King of Great Brittain, touching the affair of Bantam, and other controversies at Macassar, and on the coast of Mallabar and at Gamron, in the Gulf of Persia. Likewise a justification in anwser to the several memorials lately given unto the States General by the Marques of Albeville, touching Meslepatam and other places in the Indies. Translated out of Dutch by a good friend, for the satisfaction of all such as are impartial judges of the matters now in dispute between the two companies.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 200 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46402</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1258A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217123</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828823</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828823</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33255</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46402)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33255)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1969:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A justification of the directors of the Netherlands East Indie Company As it was delivered over unto the high and mightly lords the States General of the United Provinces, the 22th of July, 1686. Upon the subject and complaint of Mr. Skelton, Envoye Extraordinary from the King of Great Brittain, touching the affair of Bantam, and other controversies at Macassar, and on the coast of Mallabar and at Gamron, in the Gulf of Persia. Likewise a justification in anwser to the several memorials lately given unto the States General by the Marques of Albeville, touching Meslepatam and other places in the Indies. Translated out of Dutch by a good friend, for the satisfaction of all such as are impartial judges of the matters now in dispute between the two companies.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5-104, 41, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year 1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title "To the High and Mighty Lords, the States General of the United Netherlands" has separate pagination and register.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  1648-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33255:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33255:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A JUSTIFICATION OF The Directors of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands Eaſt Indie Company.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As it was delivered over unto the High and Mighty Lords the States General of the</hi> UNITED PROVINCES, <hi>the 22<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of July,</hi> 1686.</p>
            <p>Upon the Subject and Complaint of M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> SKELTON, Envoye Extraordinary from the King of Great Brittain, touching the affair of Bantam, and other Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies at Macaſſar, and on the Coaſt of Malla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar and at Gamron, in the Gulf of Perſia.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Likewiſe a Juſtification in Anſwer to the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Memorials lately given unto the States General by the Marques of</hi> Albeville, <hi>touching Meslepatam and other Places in the Indies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of Dutch by a good Friend, for the Satisfaction of all ſuch as are Impartial Judges of the matters now in diſpute between the two Companies.</p>
            <p>Printed at London, in the Year 1687.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33255:2"/>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:33255:2"/>
                  <head>To the High and Mightie Lords The STATES GENERAL Of the United Netherlands.</head>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>High and Mightie Lords,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N obedience to your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes Letter addreſſed the 30. May 1686. unto the Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidial Chamber of the Eaſt-Indie Companie at Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, being pleaſed to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the ſayd Companie in relation to your Highneſſes Reſolution of the ſame dato, to tranſmit with the verie firſt an Information unto a certain Memorial preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Mr. Skelton, Envoy Extraordinarie of his Royal Majeſtie of Great Brittain, unto your Highneſſes the ſecond of the ſaid Month, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Buſineſſe of Bantam, and moreover contayning complaints of what paſſed in the Eaſt-Indies at Gamron, Mallabar and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſar, with demand of reparation, hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Regents (or Directors) of the ſayd Companie of this Nation, have with all due
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33255:3"/>reſpect, this to ſay: Firſt Concerning the firſt Point, ſpecifying the buſineſſe of Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, that although your Puiſſant Highneſſes may verie well remember al what hath hapned and paſſed ſince the Month of May 1683, when firſt thoſe Clamors and heavie complaints were made by Mr. Chudlie, extraordinarie Envoy, in the Aſſemblie of your Puiſſant High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and thereupon ſoon after more fully dilated and deduced by Sr. John Chardin, both <hi>viva voce</hi> and in writing: Nevertheleſſe aſſuring our ſelves that it will not be unacceptable to your Pu. Highneſſes, that the ſayd Memorial be again ſom what afreſh reiterated, the foreſaid Regents of the Eaſt-Indie Netherlands Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie wil with permiſſion of your Puiſ. High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes make a ſhort recital, firſt of what in the beginning was don here in Holland by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference and treatiſes, and alſo afterward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued and further Progreſſe thereof made in England by the L. Ambaſſador Citters, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the order given him by your Puiſ. Highneſſes, and conſequentlie of the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings held in England by Committies on both ſides, and what further was acted in the ſame, and ſo com to the Principal Matter, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate as briefly as poſſiblie may be, how unreaſonable and wholie ungrounded thoſe complaints are, which in the beginning were ſo clamorous, and then will fullie juſtifie the Goverment of Batavia in their management and proceedings in thoſe affaires.</p>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:33255:3"/>
                        <p>What Concerns the firſt, Mr. Chudlie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Envoy by his Memorial of the 25. May, of the fore-ſaid year 1683, complained to your Puiſ. Highneſſes, that the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Batavia had in a manner altogether ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie, outragiouſlie delt with the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Eaſt-Indie Companie, and by main force driven them out of their ancient place of reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence at Bantham, and that in ſo ſtrange a manner, that not any one Example (a thing rather to be buried in ſilence, then related) of the like nature can be produced, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore requiring that the ſaid Netherlandiſh Companie ſhould be obliged to draw back their Troupes out of Bantam, reeſtabliſh the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh there again, and to make reparation of the loſſes by them ſuſtayned. But Sr. John Chardin, before mentioned, who by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Engliſh Eaſt-Indie Companie was ſent hither in Commiſſion, did ſomwhat mitigate theſe complaints, apparently, becauſe they were ſo horriblie extravagant, and in ſtead of accuſing the Government of Batavia, as if they had driven the Engliſh out of Bantam, did content himſelf to ſay, that it happened through the ſuggeſtion and Counſel of Major St. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, who commanded the Netherlandiſh Troups at Bantam in Chef, and that it was he that diſpoſed the King to put forth the Engliſh out of Bantam, and although all he affirmed was without any proof, but only grounded on a Conjecture, yet that which is to be wondred
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33255:4"/>at is, that he would form a publick Memorial on ſo ſlight and weak grounds.</p>
                        <p>And although the Bewinthebbers were at that time unfurniſhed with ſuch Elucidation of matters as is requiſite, not yet having then any of their Ships returned out of India, and what they knew in the buſineſs, was by Letters only ſent in Engliſh Ships from England, where the ſaid Letters were held up ſome time, the ſeals broken and opened, and then afterward handed to the Correſpondent of the Netherlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Company at London, notwithſtanding they omitted not according to the knowledge they had attained, to give your Highneſſes In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations and Anſwers to their Complaints. Whereupon your Pu. Highneſſes having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven an Anſwer to the ſaid Chudlie and Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din (unto which the Engliſh Company in ſome paſſages of their Writing do appeal) ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with the good liking of your Pu. High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, a treatie began with the forenamed Chardin and the Netherlandiſh Companie, and the buſineſs was ſo far avanced, that on both ſides a final agreement was aſſuredly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, whereas on a ſuddaine Mr. Chudlie and Sr. John Chardin pretending to have command and order from their King to put a ſtop to the buſineſs, the foreſaid Treatiſe here was unexpectedly broken of, however was with conſent of your Pu. Highneſſes, who deſired nothing more then to compoſe and conclude, if poſſible, this matter in a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33255:4"/>way, continued in England, whereunto the Lord Ambaſſador Citters was furniſhed with full Order and Power both from your Pu. Highneſſes, as alſo from the Companie here: but hereupon the Engliſh Hightning their Demands, and as appeared afterward, even in their reply, of which ſhall be ſpoken hereafter, they avoued to have other deſignes, intending to reeſtabliſh themſelves at Bantam, unto which end in the latter part of the year 1683. they prepared a great Fleet well manned to effect the ſame; but this their deſign, as themſelves affirm, &amp; complain that they might not put it in execution, as being hindred by the now deceaſed King, of happy Memorie, hereupon this Treatiſe was ſtopt, and no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther progreſs made therein until at length, it pleaſed his ſaid Majeſty to make way for the proſecuting of the agreement preſcribed Anno 1674. between his Majeſty and this State, to wit, that the differences ſhould be determined and compoſed by Committies on both ſides, who to that end according to the foreſaid Convention were to aſſemble together at London, the which being alſo approved by your Pu. Highneſſes, there was erected a Tribunal Court, conſiſtng of eight Committies, four on each part, before whom, after that the Parties on both ſides had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times appeared about the Praeliminaries and caſes incident, it was thought meet, that all things ſhould be handled in writing, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33255:5"/>the State of the caſe ſo written, to be made by Demand, Anſwer, Reply, and Duplick (or double Reply) even to a Triplick and Quadruplick, and beſides all this there were delivered up ſuch pieces probatory as might ſerve to fortifie and maintain the caſe on the one hand, with the Confutation of the ſame on the other hand, they of the Netherlandiſh Company alſo making their Demand againſt the Demand of the Engliſh, and delivering the ſame over by way of reconvention or contrary Demand, for the fraiting of four Ships, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Netherlandiſh Companie, upon the earneſt Requeſt of the Engliſh Companie had accommodated them, amounting to thirteen thouſand nine hundred pound Starling. In ſo much that the foreſaid Peeces being delivered to the ſaid Committies to do right therein, the Englſh Commiſſaries in their vote declared, that it was their opinion and ſentence, that in ſtead of all what was demanded by the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Eaſt-Indie Companie (to wit, not only the recalling of the Netherlandiſh Troops out of Bantam, and the Territories thereof, but moreover and above to deliver up the Caſtle and City of Bantam.) The Netherlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Companie was only bound, to reeſtabliſh the ſaid Engliſh Company in Bantam, ſo, and in ſuch wiſe as was demanded by Monſieur Chardin in the Hague, and to ſettle all things in ſtate as it was before the Warr, and the Damages and Reconvention (or contrary De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33255:5"/>ſhould be reſerved.</p>
                        <p>But the Committies of this State delivering in their Advice, every one of them in order did underſtand and declare, that forasmuch as the deciſion of the caſe, which muſt be judicially determined, did depend upon the veritie of Fact, which the Engliſh Companie had charged the Netherlandiſh Companie with, and in ſpecial that the ſaid Engliſh Companie were by them driven out of Bantam, of which they could not produce the leaſt proof, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaid Engliſh Companie ought to have their Demand and Concluſion made, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up againſt the Netherlandiſh Companie, denyed them: and the ſaid Engliſh Companie to be condemned to ſatisfie the Netherlandiſh Companie for the Fraighting of the four Ships which they demand by reconvention: by which, becauſe of the ceſſation of voices, the caſe being fallen into the terms, which they were in according to the convention of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of the year 1673/4, muſt come into the hands of an Arbitrator or Compromiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, to the choſing of whom by the foreſaid agreement the time of a Month was preſcribed: but the ſaid Committies for the Deciſion on both ſides, not agreeing, for although the Engliſh Companie were plantif in convention, yet the Engliſh Commiſſaries did not propoſe a Super Arbitrator, ſo hereby the whole caſe, according to an Act paſſed and ſubſcribed on both ſides, was left in the hands of his ſaid
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33255:6"/>Majeſtie and your Highneſſes, to be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by you, according to the contents of the foreſaid Agreemtnt And this is the reaſon why the ſaid Mr. Skelton, Envoy Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, made the foreſaid Memorial and Addreſs to vour Pu. Highneſſes to doe juſtice in the caſe to the Subjects of England: Whereupon it muſt needs fall under Examination, whither the complaints which the Engliſh Company have, and ſtill doe make of the buſineſs hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened at Bantam, be grounded on ſuch ſolid Reaſons, as to oblige the Netherlandiſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie ſo to reſettle them at Bantam, as they were before the War, (for more then this was before denyed to be due to them, by the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Commiſſaries themſelves) and that with reparation of Dammages and Intereſts, which they pretend to have ſuſtained by the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands Company. Now to make this caſe to appear more clearly, forasmuch, as ſince it was firſt preſented to your Pu. Highneſſes by Mr. Chudly Extraordinary Envoy, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward more amply preſſed by Sr. John Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din, is now wholy altered, and quite of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other face: as alſo that the Netherlandiſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany hath recovred further proofs for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of what the Engliſh Company did bring in, and maintain, therefore it will be neceſſary to dive ſomewhat deeper into the matter.</p>
                        <p>The Caſe is this, Sulthan Agon, formerly King of Bantam, and Father of the preſent King now reigning, having reſolutions, both
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33255:6"/>in reſpect of his age, and other conſiderations to diſinveſt himſelf of the Government, and lead a ſtill and private life, he made over his Kingdom to his Eldeſt Son, retiring himſelf to Turtiaſſa, a place of pleaſure, about ſix miles from Bantam, and ſeated a mile from the Sea, there to ſpend the reſidue of his dayes free from publick affaires. His Son ſeated on the Throne, and having the Government of the Kingdom in his hands, forthwith ſent Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors to Batavia (accompanied for the further Splendor with a train of about 300. perſons) to give notice to the Government there of his acceſs to the Crown, and alſo to reniew their ancient Alliance, ſending alſo Ambaſſadors to England, where they were in ſuch manner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, as that thoſe of the Eaſt-Indie Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagnie by their Letter to the ſaid King of Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam in July 1682. written about two years after the yong King was come unto the Crown, ſay, that ſuch honor was given to his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, as if they been ſent from the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt King or Potentat of the World, adding in the ſaid Letter, that they did with joy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that God Almighty had brought and inveſted him on the Throne of his Kingdom of Souroſoan, that is, the Kingdom of Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, with the good wil of his Father.</p>
                        <p>And furthermore his Majeſty of Great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſent away the ſaid Ambaſſadors with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents to the young King their Maſter, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with an honourable Letter to him, all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33255:7"/>which in the Proceſs is produced, and in which he is ſtiled the famous and Illuſtrious Sulthan Abdul Cahar Aba Naſar King and Lord of the ſaid Kingdom of Souroſoan, that is of Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, adding moreover, that his Majeſty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the foreſaid Ambaſſadors with all due reſpect, according to their Character, and with entire affection, as coming from a Prince, whoſe Perſon and Amitie his Majeſty declared to have in very high eſteem, and unto whom, he judged it neceſſary to ſend over his Agent or Envoy, furniſhed with power from his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and order from the Engliſh Company, for to make a ſtrickter League with the King of Bantam, which teſtimony and proffer of Alliance was yet further reiterated in another Letter, writ by the foreſaid Engliſh Company from London the 17. July 1682. alſo produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the Proceſs. By all which then it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth undeniably unto all that are impartial; that the preſent King now ruling was acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged both by the King of Great Brittain, and by the Engliſh Company, as well in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland as in India, for the lawful Lord and King of the whole Kingdom of Bantam, and as the Succeſſor of his Father.</p>
                        <p>But forasmuch as the preſent King in the direction of the affaires of the Kingdom, did not, as it ſeems, anſwer the expectation of his Father, nor ſatisfy the humor of manie of his Subjects, there aroſe a heavie Civil War in the Kingdom, in which the malcontented
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33255:7"/>entending to caſt of the yoke from their neck as they termed it, after they had alſo drawn the Old King to their partie, who thereupon ſtrengthened himſelf in Turtiaſſa (as alſo the King now reigning did at Bantam) at length by force of armes they made themſelves Maſter of Bantham, and beſieged the yong King in his Caſtle into which he was retired, enten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to bereave him both of his Throne and life, and to ſet up a yonger Brother in his place: whereupon this King apprehending no other way of deliverance, as having moſt of the great ones of his Kingdom animated againſt him, and the Communaltie alſo his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, thought it expedient for him to make known to the General of the Councel of the Netherlandiſh Companie at Batavia, his miſerable State, and that he not onely was to exſpect the los of the Crown, but alſo a moſt cruel death: the which he ſignifyed, in moſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable wiſe, imploring their aſſiſtance: but they not judging it convenient in a caſe of ſuch importance to intrude themſelves to unadviſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, did, before they determined any thing in the leaſt about it, conclude to interpoſe their Mediation betwixt Father and Son, and to that end to ſend Ambaſſadors with letters tending to that purpoſe: But the Father in a moſt diſdaing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful manner rejecting the ſame, without vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafing to return any anſwer at all to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Batavia or their Committies, the ſaid Government did at laſt reſolue, ſeeing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33255:8"/>of the Son tending to ruin, as beeing forſaken almoſt by all, to aſſiſt him againſt the Rebels, and if poſſible to deliver him out of the miſerable eſtate into which he was brought, which alſo they did with ſuch ſucceſſe, that notwithſtanding the ſtrong oppoſition of the Enemie, we Landed our forces, rayſed the ſiege of the Caſtle in which the King was, and ſet him again upon his Throne, who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uppon both to demonſtrate how gratly he was offended with the Engliſh, who had aſſiſted his enemies, as alſo to provide for his own ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie for the future, did without any inſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Netherlandiſh Companie, command them to leave his countrie and to depart elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where with their Goods. This then beeing a true Narration of what paſſed in theſe affaires, theſe conſiderable things do preſent themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves to conſideration.</p>
                        <p>Firſt, that the Old King having made over his Kingdom to his eldeſt Son, he therely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came lawful King by his Fathers tranſport, and was acknowleged ſo to be, by the King of Great Brittain, and by them of the Engliſh Eaſt-Indie Companie.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, that he therely being lawful King, his ſubjects in taking up arms agaynſt him, were Rebels.</p>
                        <p>Thirdlie, that according to the Law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and af nations, it is not onely permitted, to be aſſiſtant unto a King, that is oppreſſed by his ſubjects, but that ſuch aſſiſtance is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouvable
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33255:8"/>and a Work of Charity and Love.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, that it is contrary to the Rule of Juſtice, to aſcribe the evil Conſequences of a lawful and worthie Act, unto him that is the Author of the ſaid Act, and not of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences.</p>
                        <p>Fifthly, that it is altogether againſt reaſon to impute the Chaſing of the English out of Bantam unto them of the Government of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavia, and to their auxiliarie Forces, becauſe it is manifeſt, that the departure of the Engliſh out of Bantam was not a neceſſary, but an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental Conſequence, the King not cauſing them to depart becauſe he was victorious (for he had ſuffered them to live there from the time he came to the Crown until the Warr, to wit, during the two years of his Reign) but only becauſe he was certain they had aſſiſted his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, beſides many other ſuſpitions he might juſtly have taken up againſt them.</p>
                        <p>But againſt this, they of the Engliſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany doe alledge, and depoſe for a real truth, that they of Batavia had raiſed and fomented the quarrels between the Old and the Young King of Bantam.</p>
                        <p>That two yeares before the Warr began they had had ſecret Negotiations with Pangeran Diepa Panerat, one of the Principal Miniſters of the young King, to bring about this their deſign.</p>
                        <p>That they afterward having got this King in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their ſnares, and moſt perfidouſly brought
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33255:9"/>him under their yoke, forthwith forced him to drive out the Engliſh.</p>
                        <p>And to make the Miniſters of the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landish Company yet the more ſuſpected and ſtincking to all the world, they undertook in the beginning of the year 1683. to repreſent unto the King of Great Brittain that the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Major St. Martin who commanded over the forces of the Netherlandiſh Company at Bantam in Chef had committed very many Enormities againſt the Factors, People and the Effects of the Engliſh Company at Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, ſo farr that they diſpoſſeſſed, and drave them out of their place of reſidence: But in ſtead that the English Company ought to have proved the Facts which are eſſential to the thing, in caſe they herein aimed to triumph, they doe not in the whole product which they made in the Proceſs thereof, ſo much as alledge the leaſt appearance either directly or indirectly, no not ſo much as conſequentially might ſerve for the verifying of the Enormities of ſuch Facts.</p>
                        <p>And although the Netherlandiſh Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny might ſtand upon the Negative, which is not neceſſary, nay many times poſſible to be proved, ſave only indirectly (for no man can in a direct manner prove that which is not) ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs to manifeſt clearly that they of the Government of Batavia are altogether blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, let us onely conſider the moral impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the foreſaid Fact, viz. that the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33255:9"/>of Batavia ſhould have raiſed and fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the queſtions and differences between the Father and the Son, as alſo the notorious falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of the ſecond Fact, namely, that the ſaid Government ſhould have forced the King to cauſe the Engliſh to depart out of Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam.</p>
                        <p>What concerns the firſt, its known to the world, that for a long time, there had been no good intelligence between the Old King and the Government of Batavia, no not ſo much as to the leaſt Correſpondence, for the latter fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themſelves much affronted and injured, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that at laſt they took up Arms againſt each other, the Warr not ending until the Son came to the Crown, ſo that they could not ſtirr up the Son againſt the Father, muchleſs foment their quarrel.</p>
                        <p>And what follie would it have been for them of Batavia, to animate the Father to Warr a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Son, foraſmuch as they lived with the Son in amitie, and as good Neighbors, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any reaſon in the leaſt to complain of his Government and conduct towards them, whereas on the contrary if the Father had got the upperhand they ſhould have been in a farr wors condition, and attracted a nieu Enemie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt themſelves.</p>
                        <p>And that they ſhould have ſtirred up the Son againſt the Father, and encouraged him to Warr, cannot be imagined by any that are in their right ſenſes, partly becauſe there by they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33255:10"/>could not expect any profit or advantage, or if they had, it would have been mixt with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaintie as to the event, and again the Son would then have endeavoured to have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand and the firſt aggreſſor, whereas on the contrary it was the Father, who thereby got ſo great advantage over the Son, burning and ruinating the City, and keeping his ſaid Son beſieged in his own Caſtle, ſo that, had it not been for the intervention and ſuccours of them of Batavia, the Father certainly would have triumphed over the Son: and put the caſe the Warr had ended according to the intention and advantage of the Son, what more could he have expected thereby, who already ſate on the Throne, and could be no greater then he was, would the Son have liſtned to ſuch coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, and engaged in a Warr againſt his Father, whoſe Intereſt conſiſted in governing his Kingdom in peace? And doth it not hence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that all theſe troubles did ariſe from them who breathed after nothing more then change? Who not being able or willing to ſubmit to the Government of the young King, revolted againſt him, with intention to thruſt him from his Throne, and to ſet up another more ſuitable to their liking and humor? Which their deſign alſo ſo farr ſucceeded, that the young King was brought to the point of looſing his Grown and Life.</p>
                        <p>Could the Government of Bantam at the beginning have with any reaſon imagined, that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33255:10"/>the young King ſhould finally have got the upperhand over his Enemies and Rebells? or that the Engliſh ſhould have intermedled with that Warr, and would have aſſiſted the Rebells againſt their own Prince, whom themſelves owned as lawful King (of which hereafter ſhall be more largely ſpoken) and he thereupon ſhould have thruſt the Engliſh out of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom?</p>
                        <p>Would they have ſtirred up the Son againſt the Father, after that the Son by ſo many la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable Letters had implored their aſſiſtance, and let it come to that extremity, that in caſe they had delayed but one day longer, he muſt have given himſelf over to his Rebels, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergon a cruel death?</p>
                        <p>In caſe the Rebels (before it was delivered by the Netherlandiſh forces) had taken the Caſtle, and murthered the King, could they have hindred, that either the old King or one of his younger Sons ſhould have obtained the Crown, and ſo managed the affaires of his Kingdom, as to take vengeance of them, that had oppoſed themſelves againſt his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns.</p>
                        <p>And if ſo be in caſes of ſuch nature place may be given to conjectures and preſumptions, is it not moſt probable, that the Engliſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have done that very thing, which they falſly impute to the Netherlandiſh Company?</p>
                        <p>They Publiſh for a certain Truth, that the young King, while the Father as yet governd
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33255:11"/>the Kingdom, aſſaſſinated their Agent and Commiſes, and that he alwayes carried himſelf as an Enemy to them, whereas on the contrary the Government of the Father was moſt grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful unto them.</p>
                        <p>Doth it then ſeem to be ſuch an ungrounded praeſumption, that they (partly to revenge themſelves of that Maſſacre, of which the King of Great Brittain in his Letter to the now King of Bantam declareth himſelf ſo ſenſible) and partly that it was much for their Intereſt, that the Son might be puld down from the Throne and put to death, and that the Father or another Brother were ſet up; they ſhould labour to kindle the fire and foment this Warr? Eſpecially hereunto concurring that they were ſo ſoon readie to join their forces to the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the Father, without which the Father could not have obtained thoſe advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, nor the Son been brought to ſuch a Laborinth.</p>
                        <p>Alſo it will clearly appear, that all the miſchief which is come to the Engliſh Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie in this buſineſt, is wholy from the bad ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of affaires by their own Men and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in Bantam?</p>
                        <p>For the King of Great Brittain and the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Companie acknowledge the young King for the alone King and Soverain.</p>
                        <p>But their Miniſters declare him to be an U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurper and a Rebel of the Father.</p>
                        <p>Their Maſters endeavour to eſtabliſh a ſetled peace with him.</p>
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:33255:11"/>
                        <p>They ſet themſelves formally againſt him as their Enemie.</p>
                        <p>Their Maſters Endeavour to oblige the Son by all means poſſible, and ſend great quantitie of all manner of Ammunition of Warr to him.</p>
                        <p>They do not only diſoblige him in all things, but even aſſiſt his Enemies with the proviſion ſent to his aſſiſtance.</p>
                        <p>Their Maſters in their fore-mentioned Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, pray that God the Creator of Heaven and Earth, would bleſs and proſper him.</p>
                        <p>They endeavour to bereave him of his Throne, and make him the moſt miſerable of men.</p>
                        <p>So that having by theſe unrighteouſs courſes brought upon themſelves to be driven out of Bantam, they now known not how to excuſe the matter.</p>
                        <p>And being diſappointed in their deſign, as fallen into the pit they digged for others, they are at their wits End and know not what to doe, ſome bodie muſt be found out upon whom to lay the blame, and the next that comes to hand is the Netherlandiſh Companie, <hi>Hic mihi turbat aquas.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>But had they ſate ſtill, or had (as they would make the world believe) kept themſelves neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tral, according to the will and footſteps of their Maſters, or had they in ſtead of helping the Old, aſſiſted the young King, theſe diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties nor queſtions had never happened.</p>
                        <pb n="24" facs="tcp:33255:12"/>
                        <p>And how can the English with any ſhew of reaſon diſpute or call in queſtion the Soverainty of the young King, ſeeing it is a known caſe, that the ſending and admitting of Ambaſſadors and Agents, together with the making of Treaties and Alliances, are true tokens of a Soveraign power, and therefore all ſuch as ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit and receive Ambaſſies, do thereby acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Soverainity of them that ſend the ſame, which is alſo further owned by proffers of Alliances and Leagues, which cannot be erected but between Soveraigns.</p>
                        <p>Now as to the ſecond Fact; to wit, that after the Netherlandish Company had got the young into their ſnares and perfidiouſly brought him under their yoke, they then ſhould have forced him to the expulſion of the Engliſh, This we have before manifeſted to be a falſe fiction: For firſt they ought not in a caſe of ſo great weight and tendency make ſuch odious and malitious poſitions, except they had clear and convincing proofs at hand: There is not any one of the Witneſſes, which the Engliſh Companie have produced, that mentions a word thereof, or that ſpeakes of ſnares in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which they of Batavia cauſed the young King to fall, or of any yoke under which, againſt all fidelity, they had brought him.</p>
                        <p>It is true, they produce in the Proceſs one Mr. Waite, ſpeaking of the departure of the Engliſh by order of the King, who relates onely of an hard conteſt between the ſaid
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33255:12"/>King and Major Sr. Martin, before that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of cauſing them to depart, could be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained from him; but being, ſaith he, alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether under the power of the Hollanders, he was neceſſitated thereunto, but beſides what might be alledged to weaken this aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he confeſſeth, that what he witneſſeth thereof is not of his own knowledge, but that he believeth it to be true upon the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of perſons of worth, which of it ſelf is enough to reject the ſame, as alſo it is very obſervable what on this ſubject the foreſaid Sr. Martin and others with him doe declare: to wit, that the Conteſt was not to diſpoſe the King to the ejection of the Engliſh, but to turn away the wrath and indignation of the King (which becauſe of their aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of his Father and the Rebels, he had taken up againſt them) and thereby to deliver them from the loſs of all their Goods yea life it ſelf, as out of revenge he had determined againſt them, which alſo was ſo taken and acknowledged by the Engliſh Compagny at Bantam, when by their Agent they returned thanks unto the Miniſters of the Netherlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Companie for their protexion. But ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the King had not been ſo incenſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, as hath been ſaid, and that he had not had deſign at all to be avenged on them, yet the mere conſideration of his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity might have moved him to their ejection, as beeing aſſured they aſſiſted his Rebels, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33255:13"/>in apprehenſion, that they as wel verſed in warkely affaires might from England or Elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where reenforce themſelves with ſhips and Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, beſides the Perillous neighbourhood of their warehouſe to his Caſtle, his Father laying round about Bantam with his armie, and keeping it yet for ſom moneths beſieged, and he as yet by his auxiliarie forces having onely the ſea open, might if he were not verie circumſpect, bee again ſuddenly aſſaulted, or at leaſt, the Engliſh remayning in Bantam by ſpying all opportunities, make diſcoveries to the enemies, ſo as in way of providence it was requiſite for him to do what he did.</p>
                        <p>If the Letters, (brought in the Proceſſe) be reviewed, it wil appear, whither it be true, as is imputed to them, that they of their own mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did ſend ſuccours to the ſaid King, yea ſo as thereby (if their moſt injurious aſperſion were true) to get him into their Klutches or on the contrarie, that is was don at the Great and inſtant entreaties of the young King, after that al wayes of reconciliation had in vain bin attempted.</p>
                        <p>But foraſmuch as this aſſiſtance and ſuccour is thus averſlie and after ſo odious a manner de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, it will be neceſſaire to relate the ſame ſomewhat more fully, and more clearly to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the occaſion and progreſſe thereof.</p>
                        <p>After the Rulers of Batavia had ripely conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted about the conſtitution of the affaires of the young King, they thought meet, as alſo hath before bin ſpecified; to proffer their ſervice of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33255:13"/>Mediation, between the Father and the Son, to which end they wrote two Letters in civil and obliging termes, teſtifying their purpoſe and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in a way of frindſhip to accommodate and lay by their queſtions and differences, and with that Intention ſent thir Plenepotentiaries with Letters, the one to the Father, and the other to the Son in a Ship prepared to that end, after that ſom dayes before by way of advance they had alſo ſent three other Ships, but conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thoſe Plenipotentiaries went unto a place where the parties on both ſides were in armes, and not being certain whither they might meet with friends or enemies, they therfore judged themſelves obliged to put them into a poſture of defence, furniſhing them with weapons in caſe of neceſſitie to make reſiſtance to ſueh, as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting the right of nations (eſpecially in that confuſed ſtate of things) and the reſpect that ought to be given to publick Perſons, might poſſiblie attempt to lay hold on and injurie them, and this is that fleet of Ships and Barcks which in theſe and other of their writings they ſo much enhance and make a ſtir about, as ſent to Bantam to land our Troupes there.</p>
                        <p>Our forefayd Plenepotentiaries having way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſome time for an anſwer from the old King, received none, and not knowing what properly the intention of theſe men might as be to them, ſent a good troop of men, to inform themſelves more exactly of the State of things: but being a little advanced, they met ſome Europeans,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33255:14"/>who by an Engliſh Man enquired of them, wherefore they came to intermeddle with the differences of the two Kings? whereuppon being anſwered, that they came as friends to procure a peace between the Father and the Son, they ſoon perceyved the deſign they had formed agaynſt them, for forthwith they ſaw a great troop of men gathered together, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king readie ſome fire Ships and other veſſels fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for warre, making a ſhew as if they would fal foule with us, who verilie were to few in number to have thoughts to attempt any thing agaynſt ſo powrful an enemie, who ſeemed to come agaynſt them, which alſo they did and came to the deed it ſelf, ſhooting at us, and with their Canons, which were Managed by the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, they much endammaged our Ships, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they perceived, that they not onely, did not accept of our Mediation, but alſo that they treated us as enemies: upon which they of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravia ſoon reſolved by force of arms to deliver the young King out of this Miſerie and the brinke of death, and to this end to ſend a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient power of Ships and Men to this aſſiſtance, which alſo had that ſucceſſe, as before is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</p>
                        <p>The aſſiſtance which the Engliſh gave to the old King, whereby the diſpleaſure and wrath of the young King was ſo kindled agaynſt them, even to their ejection out of his country, is ſo notoriously known to the world, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the proofs which the Netherlandish Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Panie
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33255:14"/>have alreadie alledged, they yet further could bring hundreds of convincing teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, but let onely the letters of the young King which he ſent from his beſieged caſtle to them of Batavia be produced, and you shal hear him complayning in theſe formal words.</p>
                        <q>
                           <p>
                              <hi>What reaſon hath the English Captain to help to shoot at me, without once laying to hart that he is reſident in my Land and Zea, this is yet worſe that Mr. Boyer (one of the English Marchants at Bantam) cauſes my houſe to be shot at, not once thinking, that I deſired the King of England that he might be Captaine in the English Lodge: Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of Capitain Moor Speelman, that he wil warn the English not to com on shore, to shoot at my houſe, and aſſiſt mine enemie alſo with powder, forasmuch as he hath his reſidence in my Land, but not in the Land of Sultan Agon (the old King) as alſo to perſwade them not to follow mine enemie, ſeeing they drink my water and dwel in my Land, and that they cloſe no more with Sultan Agon; if Captain Moor have love for me, let him be pleaſed forceably to Inſinuate this unto the English, that above all things they shoot not at my houſe, nor betake themſelves to Land.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </q>
                        <p>The which alſo in a following Letter to the Major St. Martin he further confirmed.</p>
                        <p>Beſide the ſaid King did afterward make often Complaints to the whole World, that the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh had given all aſſiſtance to his enemies: yea one of the Engliſh themſelves, relates in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain book printed at London, in which he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33255:15"/>gives an account of what paſſed at Bantam du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the warre, and of which he was eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, viz. that they of the Engliſh nation had furniſhed the old King with moſt of all the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition he had, and withal, that they uſed all means poſſible to encourage and encenſe the Javans againſt the Dutch: and thereupon he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, that they (to with the Engliſh) had no ground much to rely upon the frienſhip of the Netherlanders, in caſe they once came to ſet foot on land: Notwithſtanding they are not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to deny al this, yea in the Memorial deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by Mr. Chardin (while he was here) and ſeconded and further confirmed by a certain Memorial, which the Engliſh Companine, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with their demands, delivered over to the Commiſſaries, who were to decide on both ſides, namely, that the Engliſh in all this while, had kept themſelves altogether neutral between the ſaid oppoſing parties, and conclude from thence, that the King had not out of his motion cauſed them to depart, but thro the Inſtigation of the Major St. Martin (a thing moſt notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous falſe) as at the beginning they clamoured and publiſhed to the whole world, namely that we drave them out with force, after a moſt barbarous and unheard of manner.</p>
                        <p>So then it appeares on both ſides that their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture was cauſed by the Kings order, who only hath powr of Command in his country, and whoſe command they were bound to obey: But it is denyed, and there is reaſon to proteſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33255:15"/>againſt Injurie don us, as if we had bin the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of the ſame. Ought not then the Engliſh to prove that fact? undoubtedly yea; but have they any proof thereof? certainly non at al. Can the Engliſh Satisfy with this, that in ſtead of proof they onely produce obſcure, ſuſpicious diſcourſes to which no credit wil be given<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſave only by ſuch as are praeoccupied, and readie to take, whatever may ſerve to feed and ſtreng then an anticipated humour.</p>
                        <p>They remonſtrate, that in a certain hearing, which the King of Bantam granted them ſoon after the obtained Victorie; they could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the leaſt diſtemper, or Indignation, but that indeed there were ſome hot words paſſed between the King and Sr. Martin: But, I pray, is this a proof to convince as to a crime, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of ſuch nature as this? We neither may nor can rely upon the geſture and countenance of any, muchleſs of a King, eſpecially of an Indian Prince, who ſeeks to keep in his wrath and indignation, and to take his beſt opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to avenge himſelf: Is there any one that ever heard that Major Sr. Martin inſtigated the King to chaſe the English? Is there any thing produced in the leaſt tending thereto? Certainly nothing: on the contrarie the ſaid Sr. Martin as a Man of honor, a Gentleman of qualitie, and ſurpaſſing modeſtie, wiſdom and learning, wholie takes of all ſiniſter ſuſpition, in proteſting that the intercourſe with the King was entended to no other end, then to divert and take of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33255:16"/>King from the deſign he had to deſtroy all the Engliſh, and ſhould he not to doe ſo, have had much more reaſon, then, as the Engliſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie in their Demand given in againſt the Netherlandiſh Companie, and more amply in their Reply doe aſſert, that he ſome years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had cauſed the Agent of the English Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie to be murthered, together with their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, of which they afterwards made ſuch heavie complaints, yet nothing followed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon: Is it then to be wondred at, that he was ſo greatly incenſed becauſe of this their action, that except he had forceablie bin diſwaded by Sr. Martin, he had cauſed them all to be ſlain? They endeavour alſo to make the Netherlandiſh Companie or their Miniſters ſuſpected to have an hand, likewiſe in this Action, but they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to proteſt againſt this outragious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurie and Calumnie, They who at the ſame time were ſo highly out of favour with the old King then reigning, would certainly be far from having an hand in ſo horrible a Murther, by which they could not in any reſpect be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantaged: If that William Kaef the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh Reſident at Bantam, when the Old King overthrew and ſaccaged the Citie, was fain for to eſcape maſſacring, to retire to Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavia leaving all the Goods and Effects of the Netherlandiſh Compagnie in their Lodge, which undoubtedly was by ſome Engliſh, though perhaps without the knowledge of their Maſters in part ſtolen: ſhould not then
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33255:16"/>the Engliſh, had they not in that furie been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected by the Netherlandish forces, have been in far greater danger? Would there have bin any appearance for any of them to have eſcaped with their lives? And nevertheleſs according to their ſaying, It is the Dutch that cauſed all theſe Troubles and Miſchiefs to befal them. But the Engliſh were not then of that opinion, nor uſed ſuch kind of Language, when they came ſo ſolemnly to declare their thankfulneſs to the Dutch, for their good will and protection they had ſhewed to them.</p>
                        <p>But how little the Engliſh Companie doth agree with it ſelf, and how often they are out and in in their writings, doth hereby appear, that in what they have depoſed by form of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, themſelves ſay, that their Agent and the Councel the day after the raiſing of the Siege, were with the King in his Caſtle, to take of and appeaſe, if poſſible, the Chagrin and wrath of the King ſo hot againſt them, and that they then found him by far leſs incenſed then the Hollanders ſaid he was: Farthermore in their ſaid Memorial, which they delivered over, together with the foreſaid pretences, and to which by the foreſaid Demand they adhere, they ſay, that the ſame day they were introduced to the King, who laid before them many accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, not ſo much as permitting them to ſpeak a word for their defence.</p>
                        <p>It followeth then, that whereas they ſaid, when they were brought in before him, they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33255:17"/>could not in the leaſt perceive in his poſture or viſage any token of indignation, is a pure un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth.</p>
                        <p>But yet further to convince the Engliſh Company of the falſehood of what they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute to the Netherlandiſh Companie, and that after ſo odious a manner, it is only needful to look over the Anſwer of the Netherlandish Companie to the complaints brought in by Mr. Chudley and Sr. John Chardin, in May 1682. whereby the ſame doth teſtifie a ſuper-abounding affection and perfect readineſs to contribute to all meanes and wayes of reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of the English Company there, by em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying their Credit and Authoritie with the preſent King, as alſo to reconcile the two contending parties, according to a <hi>Medium</hi> therein propoſed, and ſo conſequently to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal our Troups out of the Kingdom of Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam.</p>
                        <p>Now it can eaſily be conceived, they would not have done all this, in caſe that by their meanes that Warr had been raiſed, or that they had had an hand in the chaſing of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish, or had cauſed the ſame, muchleſs if it had been true, as is malitiouſly imputed to them, that for many yeares ſince they had plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for to draw, and by that meanes to engroſſe the whole Pepper-Trade unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and that as they affirm, to the ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable dammage of the English Compagnie, of which ſhall be further ſpoken hereafter.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33255:17"/>And ſeeing then it is a falſe Fiction, that the Dutch Companie ſhould have driven the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish out of Bantam, although perhaps it might have been (which nevertheleſs was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver directly nor indirectly attempted) that by ſuggeſtion they might have ſomewhat contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted thereunto; yet hereby alſo their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded action of dammage and reparation doth fall of it ſelf.</p>
                        <p>But that of which alſo, they have made an hideous cry and tintamar, by an expreſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint in their foreſaid Memorial, which in May 1683. they preſented to your Puiſſ. Highneſſes, and which they more fully dilated afterward, is firſt, that the day after the deliverance of the King, one James de Roy, Lieutenant of the Companie of Major St. Martin, ſhould have taken down the Flag named the Banner of St. George, planted upon the Houſe of one Captain John Fiſher, that the ſaid Fiſher thereupon making haſte to his Houſe found the ſaid de Roy with a part of the Flag in his hand, having torn the reſt, and given it to his Souldiers to make Scarfs of.</p>
                        <p>Again the ſaid Souldiers had drunk out part of the Drinking-wares, and taken away the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder together with his houshold-ſtuff, and withall evilly entreated him, and placed ſome black Moores in his houſe.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, that five dayes after the departure of the English from Bantam, our Souldiers came into the Houſe of the English Companie,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33255:18"/>and had ſent ſome Moores (of their Servants) to fetch of the Pavillion that was diſplaid on their Lodge.</p>
                        <p>Now ſuppoſe all this to be a true ſtorie, and might thereupon give credit at the depoſition of one man only, to wit, the foreſaid Captain Fiſher, and that alſo in his own caſe, for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Witneſſes are not brought for proof of this Fact, yet it is conſiderable the Actor hier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was in ſervice of the King, and not as is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry abuſively ſaid, the Lieutenant of Major Sr. Martin, and conſequently the Souldiers were Bantamers: and it is worthie of obſervation, foraſmuch as this Jaques de Roy is ſo ofsen brought upon the Stage, that he is a perſon, who ſomewhile before the Warr, was retired from Batavia to Bantam, for to ſhun his Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, whom the young King took into his ſervice, who had in and during the Warr ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalized himſelf by ſpecial ſervices, wherefore alſo he was highly eſteemed by the ſaid King, though himſelf were a man of little worth.</p>
                        <p>Again, although the foreſaid firſt Flag (for there is mention made of two) might have been the Banner of St. Gerge, yet could it not bring any reſpect to a private Houſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to be freed from the diſorders that in time of Warr are incident, more then to any other Houſe, &amp; what concerns the Banner &amp; uſe made thereof, is that a thing to cauſe ſo much diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, that a Captain of the King ſhould with his Souldiers take down from a private Houſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33255:18"/>the English Flag, after that the King and the whole Nation lookt on him as an Enemie of his Perſon and of the State?</p>
                        <p>What concerns the ſecond part, although the relation thereof might perhaps be accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to trueth, which nevertheleſs is doubted of, and cannot be prooved, it doth not touch the Dutch Companie, yea though it had been don by their Men: but muſt be imputed to the diſorders in War.</p>
                        <p>As to the third point, if the recital thereof be according to trueth, and that they ſent ſome of their black Servants to take down the Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, which notwithſtanding is nothing but a report and recital of ſome Chineſes, this doth nothing to the charging of the Netherlandish Companie, the ſaid Chineſes might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, how they came to know thoſe Moores were Servants of the Dutch Souldiers and not of the King, as is much more probable, ſeeing it ſhould be an unuſual thing, at leaſt unheard of among us, that ſimple Souldiers should have Moores to their Servants: but po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſito that the Dutch Souldiers might have been Executors of the Kings Order therein: the Kings Right is inconteſtable, and he might take away the Pavillion of the English, after that he had banished them out of his Countrie, yea though the Souldiers had don it without the Order of the King, which is not likely, yet had it been nothing elſe then a Militarie Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, which alſo muſt be aſcribed to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33255:19"/>of War, where the Lawes of Modeſty and Deceneie are ſeldom regarded, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without injuſtice cannot be imputed to them, who in the time of the War at Bantam did repreſent the Government of Batavia, who never were behinde hand, in that reſpect which they ow to Crowned Heads; but what need is it to have recours to conjectures, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as by a certain produced depoſition it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, that it was the King himſelf who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Flag to be taken down from the English Lodge: and what is ſaid of the Dutch Flags which after the Victorie were planted upon the Caſtle and in other parts of the City, deſerves no Anſwer, ſince its a known thing that we never pretended any territorial Right in Bantam, muchleſs put the ſame in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but however the ſaid Flags ſerved to no other purpoſe, then to make it known to the Dutch Troupes, who after the raiſing of the Siege, were poſted in the principal places of the City according to the uſual practiſe every where in like occaſions. The Flag upon the Caſtle was ſet up by order of the King to ſhew honor to the Dutch, however placed under the Flag of the King.</p>
                        <p>Beſides they of the Engliſh Company com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, that the day after the raiſing of the ſiege, the Dutch Reſident Kaeff with a Troop of Souldiers and ſome Maſons came into the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Lodge, and ordered the Engliſh Agent forthwith to take away the Galeries, and to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33255:19"/>naile up the Windowe: And that thereupon a Dutch Renegate, who was in his Company, began preſently to threaten him, that if the English did not, he himſelf would do it, which alſo, as they ſay, he really did.</p>
                        <p>This ſeemeth to be an outragious act don to the English: but if we look into the nature of the thing, it will be found to be a meer trifel, which they ought to be aſhamed to urge in this manner:</p>
                        <p>The Hiſtorie is this: Becauſe the Dutch Companie would not be troubleſom to any, they choſe their own Lodge at Bantam for their Magaſin of Arms, and other proviſions. Now the Wall of their ſaid Lodge touching part of the Engliſh Compagnies dwelling Houſe, and in that ſaid Wall they formerly had had no other opening beſide a caſement: Somewhile af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the English by permiſſion of the Old King, who let ſlip no opportunitie to affront &amp; moleſt them, made great wide windows, to open and ſhut, and beſides that a Gallirie alſo which hanging four or five foot over the ground of the Hollanders Lodge, gave the Engliſh oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to hear and ſee all what ever the Dutch did: The young King conſidering that our ſaid Lodge in time of Warr, was like to be the great Magaſin, thought it requiſite to prevent ſuch dangerous conſequences as might be occaſioned by overtures, being over a place of the Houſe, where the Powder and other Ammonitions of Warr did lay, and out or through which win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33255:20"/>or overtures in the wall, the English at all times might com upon that place, at their pleaſure: and knowing the English would not ſeale up thoſe Windowes, nor ſuffer the Galli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to be taken away, he thereupon ſent his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants with a Dutch Renegado, to cauſe it to be don; and it may perhaps be true, that the Reſident Kaeff was at that time preſent, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it was don in the ſaid Lodge of the Dutch Companie, where according to his Office he was to take care of the Magaſin.</p>
                        <p>What evil can herein be imputed to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, and what accuſation can the Engliſh frame from this? A thing which way ſo ever they take it, was carried on by the authoritie of the King, and according to their ſaying executed by a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negado, the verie naming of whom ſhews, that he was not in ſervice nor under the Oath of the Netherlandiſh Companie.</p>
                        <p>And what beſides this they lay to the Charge of the duteh Companie, is, firſt that they ſhould have taken from the English their horſes, and ſom other things, and have eonſtrayned them to take out the Powder that was in their Ships and to bring it a ſhore.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, that what they, at the command of the King to depart, in al haſte had laden in their boats to bring aboard their Ships, in which neyther the people of the Countrie, nor the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers did any wayes hinder them, but paſſing by the Engliſh Chalops which kept the watch at ſea, they were by them arreſted, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33255:20"/>they had order to ſuffer nothing to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried aboard the Engliſh Ships, and in caſe they perſiſted to do it they ſhould be ſhot at, by which they ſhould have bin neceſſitated to return to Land with their Boats.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly that they complaying of ſuch vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to Major St. Martin, he in a jeſting way ſhould anſwer, that al was don by order from the King, whereas no man on Land, Soldier or others had a hand in thoſe Violences, but all was don by our Soldiers onely.</p>
                        <p>Forthly, that the Chief of the French requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the King reſtitution of four Chiſts with Silver which was taken from him, the King ſhould anſwer in the preſence of the Dutch Commiſſarie, that he knew nothing thereof, and that he would do no injurie neither to them, nor to the Engliſh, Danes, or other Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers trafficking in his Countrie, and in caſe any wrong had bin don unto him, ſince the Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders had ſet foot on Land, that he muſt require reparation from the Duth Commiſſarie, or the General at Batavia.</p>
                        <p>Fiftly, that at the laſt inſtance made, to cauſe the Engliſh to quit Bantam, being, as they ſay, the day before their departure, our Soldiers came into the Engliſh Lodge, robbed the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and took away all they found there; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the people of the country (ſo far were they from doing them the leaſt wrong) permitted them to ſeal up their Magaſin and undertook to keep it ſafe for them.</p>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:33255:21"/>
                        <p>What Concerns the firſt point, ſorasmuch as they do not onely not ſay, much leſſe prove, that our men ſhould have taken the horſes and and other goods from the Engliſh, nor that they ſhould have conſtrained them to fetch their powder out their Ships, therefore the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh Companie wil paſſe that by, as a thing which doth not concern them, and of which they are wholy diſcharged by the often fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Memorial annexed to the demand or pretenſe which the Engliſh Companie depoſed and delivered in, and to which they do referre themſelves, in which is expreſſely ſaid, that Pagoran Diepa Panerat, one of the principal Miniſters of the young King, or rather the firſt Miniſter of State, had don the ſame, although they put it in ſuch General and ambiguous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, in all appearence, as if they would lay it to the Charge of our Men: Onely what concerns the Powder, the Dutch companie doth ſay, that in caſe it were true, that the Engliſh were fain by the order of the King to unlade the ſame and bring it to Land, that it was don not becauſe the King ſtood in need of it, for he was abundantly furnished by them of Batavia, but only to prevent that they might not deliver the ſame to his enemies, and beſides it cannot be ill taken, that the King in that confuſed ſtate of things, would oppoſe and hinder the Engliſh from going ſo often too and fro to their Ships.</p>
                        <p>Concerning the ſecond point, namely that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33255:21"/>we ſhould have hindred the Engliſh from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting out of Bantam, and alſo to have ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped their boats, hath not the leaſt appearance of truth in it, foraſmuch as themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that we aſſiſted them with our Boats and Chalops to carrie their goods and wares a bord their Ships, when none of the people of the countrie, or their Boats could be obtained to be ſerviceable to them therein, ſo little accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance they had with that Nation, and how can this hang together, that we ſhould have procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their departure from the King, and then when they were readie to depart, to hinder it, yea the Engliſh diſagree in the verie poſition laid down about it, for their foreſaid Memoriall, to which by their demand, they refer themſelves, dictates not that their men were ſtopt at Sea by our Barks that kept watch, but that it was don by the watch of the Netherlandiſh Companie on Land at the mouth of the haven, to wit, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving order to ſuffer nothing to be carried from Land to the Engliſh Ships.</p>
                        <p>The complaints which thereupon they ſhould have made to Major St. Martin comprehended in the third point, as if he had in a kind of mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, anſwered them, that all was don by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the King, what doth this make to the thing? for put the caſe the ſaid Major (which not withſtanding is not granted) might ſay, not in way of Mockage, but in earneſt, that it was to be imputed to the order of the King, which goes farther, if thoſe orders had bin executed by our
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33255:22"/>Soldiers, although that alſo is denyed, and of which the Engliſh doe produce no proofs, yet could it not any wayes prejudice the Dutch Companie as not being bound to be reſponſable for the Orders of the King.</p>
                        <p>Touching the Kings anſwer to the Chief of the French his complaint, and that the King remitted him as to that matter to Batavia, of which is ſpoken in the forth point, although it ſhould be al true, which notwithſtanding is not proeved, it might be that the King did it in ſuch a manner to free himſelf from the trouble of thoſe complaints, as wel knowing that one of his Miniſters had ceaſed on the ſaid Chefts with ſilver, which however it be, neither concerns the English, nor obligeth the Dutch Companie to be anſwerable for the ſame.</p>
                        <p>But to demonſtrate yet more fully how far the English Companie in all their pretences do aberre from the truth, they ſay, as may be ſeen, in the propoſall of the firſt point, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Countrie, to wit, of Bantam, the day before they, viz. the English were cauſed to remove, did indeed com into their Lodge, but without doing of them the leaſt Injurie, and yet they ſay in their foreſaid Memorial anexed to their Demand, that at the ſame time they took away all their proviſion driving the English out of the Chambers (except one named, Waite) and took poſſeſſion thereof; but a little after the Dutch Soldiers came who further made ſpoil, and carried away al they found there: But this
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33255:22"/>can not be: becauſe the Engliſh had a day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their departure carried away for Batavia in the Ships of the Dutch Company all their Moveables, to the very leaſt thing of any worth (their departure, as themſelves ſay, being the 12. of April) and ſo nothing could be found: and beſides all the time of their inhabiting of Batavia. which dured more then a year, they never brought in any complaints, by a Liſt or other way ſhewing, what the Dutch Souldiers had rob'd them of, but on the contrary they came and rendred their thancks to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there, for all the aſſiſtance had been don unto them, without the leaſt mention of wrong received: which had they don, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment there might forthwith have cauſed enquirie to be made, and if it had been true, procured ſatisfaction; but letting that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſlip, and being negligent therein, and then to bring in their Complaints hier, and that without any proof, the Dutch ſay is a thing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unreaſonable.</p>
                        <p>As hath before been alledged, the Engliſh Compagny from the beginning hath pretended reeſtablishment at Bantam from the Dutch Companie, and to which in their Demand or Memorial of their pretences delivered over to the Commiſſaries of both ſides, they remain perſiſting, with requeſt that the ſame may in the firſt place before all other things be deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and determined, taking for their founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that that reeſtablishment had alreadie bin
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33255:23"/>accorded and agreed to by you Pu. Highneſſes and by the Netherlandish Company.</p>
                        <p>But now not yet content with that, they praetend by their foreſaid Demand beſides the recalling of the Dutch Troops, the delivering over the Caſtle of Bantam in its entire, for to put into it a ſtrong Garriſon, pretending that otherwiſe they would not be willing to ſettle themſelves again there, yea they require that the whole Citie be delivered up, and put into the hands of his Majeſty of Great Brittain.</p>
                        <p>What concerns the firſt, it is true indeed that the English Company did pretend all this, but it is evident, that the Dutch Company hath as little right to this, as to give over the whole City with the Caſtle, according to their fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pretence: We who have only a ſimple re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence, without participation of any Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which doth wholie reſide in the perſon of the King, it is for us a moral impoſſibility to diſpoſe of that which <hi>Privative</hi> doth belong to the King, and ſo to reeſtablish the English there againſt his will without intruſion into his right, and violating his Authority: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Dutch Company hath their Troops in Bantam which ſerve the King for a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon to defend his City, yet that affords them no Territorial right, nor the leaſt power to bring in again thoſe whom he hath baniſhed from thence.</p>
                        <p>And as they cannot by force of Arms oblige the King to take in again the English, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſettle
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33255:23"/>them in Bantam without uſurping upon the Right of Nations, and deſervedly to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre the diſaffection and hatred of all the Princes and Potentates of Indie, ſo can they with as little ground do it by threatnings, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out injurie to their fidelity, which muſt be the ſtay of the credit of the ſaid Companie among the Indian People, who otherwiſe would not rely upon their word, nor enter into Alliances, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nd combinations with them.</p>
                        <p>But they of the Engliſh Company averre, that herein not only conſiſts their intereſt, but they have alſo the promiſe of your Pui. High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, they onely requiring the Execution of the ſame.</p>
                        <p>As to their Intereſt the Dutch Company will eaſilie grant, that the foreſaid reeſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might be for their advantage (although they, as hath before bin ſaid, declare that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they have a Garriſon, and the Caſtle for their ſecurity they would not reſide there) ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo undoubtedly it would be for their intereſt, if the Dutch Company did admit them into thoſe Countries, where we have our ſpices, and which we poſſeſs by propriety, with ſecluſion of all others: and ſo alſo it would be for the intereſt of this State and the Inhabitants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that the Engliſh would permit them the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation and trade in the Barbados, Caribes, New-England, the Virgines, and many other Countries they poſſeſs in America, where they will not ſuffer us, nor other Nations of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33255:24"/>ſo much as to paſs their Seas. But the Queſtion in this caſe is not, the convenience or Intereſt but the Right. If that the Engliſh Company could groundedlie maintain, that the Dutch Company is bound to reſettle them there, and prove it by cleare and convincing reaſons that they had driven them out of Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, the buſineſs were at an end.</p>
                        <p>But to come to their ſecond ground, viz. the promiſe of your Pui. Highneſſes, and of the Dutch Company, which was made to them Anno 1683<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they ſhould be reſetled there: To this we have before ſaid, and do now again anſwer, that thoſe Proffers do ſerve for an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable proof, that the Dutch Companie ſought nothing more then to continue with the Engliſh Company in an intimate Friendſhip and Confidence, which by that accident at Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam did ſeem in ſome meaſure to be interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and that they would rather decline the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages which by ſuch exceſſive expences they had acquired there, then to remain continually in contention and quarrel with the Engliſh Company: and hereby the Dutch Company oblitterate thoſe aſpenſions and calumnies im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted unto them, as if in all appearance they for their own Intereſt and wilfully had incited and fomented the Differences, and warr that followed thereupon, between the Father and the Son, and had two yeares before formed that deſign by correſponding with Pangoran Diepa Nagara, and ſo contrived the baniſhing of the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:33255:24"/>Engliſh out of Bantam: For if all this had bin true, they ſhould verie badly have managed their buſineſs, after that all was thus ſucceeded, and they with ſuch exceſſive charges attained what they aimed at, they ſhould then without any preſſing neceſſitie have made ſo little ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it, and that for the mere pleaſure of them, who for all the pretences, and juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of their complaints made, had nothing to ſhew in way of proof: Indeed had the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Company, at that time reſted ſatisfyed, the Dutch Companie ſhould have been obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to perform the ſame, how praejudiciable ſoever it might afterward have been to them: But foraſmuch as the Engliſh Company was then pleaſed wholie to reject and break of thoſe tranſactions, whereas we ſo deſirouſly longed that they might be brought to a good end in England, and for which, as is ſaid, the Lord Ambaſſador Citters was fully authoriſed, al the time that buſineſs of Bantam was in the termes, as they were, during the Negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and treatie with Mr. Chudly and Sr. John Chardin in the Hague, and which the Engliſh Company alſo cauſed to be broken of: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it fals now to be enquired into, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Dutch Companie, ſince the caſe of things be wholie changed and of an other nature, be ſtill obliged to the ſame.</p>
                        <p>It is evident that at that time the State of the affaires of Bantam was not known, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely, whither the warr between the Father
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33255:25"/>and the Son were yet remaining, or ended; if it were determined, whither by an accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation or by the Sword: If by the Sword, who of the two, the Father, or Son, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained Conqueror, and thereby become ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Kingdom: During which uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie, it can not be judged imprudencie, that the Netherlandiſh Eaſt-Indie Company (by whoſe forces the Son was delivered from his inevitable ruin, and by whom he further was to be aſſiſted, ſo as not to fall under the oppreſſion of his rebellious Subjects) ſhould interpoſe their credit and authority by the ſaid King for the ſetling of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish in Bantam, if he were Conqueror, and with condition the English ſhould yield no further aſſiſtance to the Father: and in caſe the Father were Victor, that then the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish ſhould imploy all their credit by the Father, that the Dutch Company might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy a good Neighborhood with them: and theſe Proffers of the Dutch Companie, while things ſtood thus at an uncertaintie, were the more excuſable by the King of Bantam, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they endeavoured thereby to prevent the ſuccours which the English Company pretended to ſend the Father, and alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe at that time it was not yet known, how far the English had made themſelves irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilable to him.</p>
                        <p>During this uncertaintie of things, the Dutch Companie made theſe Proffers, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="51" facs="tcp:33255:25"/>Sr. John Chardin himſelf projected an accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation between both the Companies, in which mention was made of the withdrawing of the Dutch Troopes out of Bantam, and what each Companie ſhould be obliged unto in thoſe occaſional accidents, as are thereby ſpecifyed: But as it pleaſed the ſaid Mr. Chudly and Sr. John Chardin very unexſpectedly to break of thoſe treatiſes, which already were ſo far advanced, and they alſo of the English Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany on their part did reject the Proffers, which not only your Puiſ: Highneſſes in their foreſaid Anſwer to the Memorial of Sr. John Chardin, had made: But thoſe alſo, which the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor Citters afterwatds did make, in the name and upon the account of the Netherlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Companie, after that the foreſaid Sr. John Chardin was returned into England, and the Engliſh began again to bring in new Demands, after they had very diſdaingfully rejected the former, hereupon the Netherlandiſh Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny judged, that they ſtood no longer bound to theirs, eſpecially when as ſomewhile after by tydings on both ſides in Letters from the Indies it was ſignifyed, that the Warr at Bantam was ended to the advantage of the young King, who reobtained the Kingdom as poſſeſſor, had taken the Father priſoner and ſubdued his Rebels, ſo that conſequently the Netherlandiſh Company had now no longer any ground nor pretext, either to treat with the Engliſh about their reſetling in Bantam, as beeing, <hi>Territorium
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33255:26"/>plane alienum,</hi> muchleſs to promiſe the ſame, and the rather becauſe the now reigning King having conſidered the conſpiracies of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish with his Father and rebellious Subjects, hath declared them his pernicious Enemies.</p>
                        <p>Seeing then from all what hath been ſaid, it clearly appeareth, that the English Companie did rather choſe to expect the uncertain Lot of Warr, then to agree with the Dutch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, while it was time, about their Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement, it is therefore reaſonable that they now acquieſce, and leave the Netherlandiſh Company unmoleſted, as to their reeſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                        <p>It followeth therefore, that it is wholy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the purpoſe, at preſent to make uſe, or apply to their advantage the foreſayd anſwer of your Pu: Highneſſes to the foreſaid Memorial, after they had rejected the foreſaid Proffer, and had determined not onely to reeſtabliſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by force of Arms, but wholie to becom the Maſters of Bantam, and to that end to ſet out a formidable Power of ſhips and Men at ſea, though their Entreprize, as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves depoſe in their foreſaid reply, was ſtopt by his Majeſty of happie Memorie, &amp; not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to put forth to ſea: now this was the reaſon that they having formed &amp; being buſie about this deſign, that the Charges thereof might not be fruitleſſe, did not only reject the Proffers a foreſayd, of the Dutch Companie, but made ſuch Exceſſive Extravagant demands, as
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33255:26"/>the delivering up of the whole Citie of Bantam with the Caſtle, although they wel knew that it neither would nor could bee accepted of us, or in caſe they were accepted, that then they had attaind to what they aymed.</p>
                        <p>So long then as the State of things was at an uncertaintie, and it might be in doubt who of the twain father or ſon ſhould have the upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, though the ſonne ſeemd by far more like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to prevail, nevertheleſſe the Netherlands Companie judged, that in ſuch a Conſtitution of things, it could not be il taken that they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred with the English Companie into a treatic, how they might after the beſt way procure a peace between the two Kings, by interpoſing their credit and ſervice of love, &amp; obtain the reeſtablishment of the Engliſh Companie; but al this being rejected by the Engliſh with diſdaing, and that uncertaintie which then was, beeing brought to a Certaintie, ſo as the whole buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is becom of quite another Nature, that the Netherlandiſh Companie ſhould yet be bound to perform, what they in the uncertain ſtate of things did ſhew themſelf willing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, the Netherlandiſh Companie apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, that it in juſtice cannot be required. For firſt thereby, beſides other conſiderations, they ſhould certainly be made looſers of the ſum of ſix times hundred thouſand Ryxdallers, which the King of Bantam by evening acounts is found endebted to the Dutch Companie, and of which a Contract is made with him in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:33255:27"/>in which he grants to their Company the Traffick in his Kingdom, ſo long and until, he ſhall come to be in a condition to repay the ſame to the Dutch Company: But that which beſides this deſerves to be reflected upon, is, that the King of Bantam hearing a rumour that the Engliſh Company perſiſted in their pretence of reſettlement in Bantam, with the calling back of our Troopes thence, wrote to the Government of Batavia (even after he had ſurmounted al difficulties) that in caſe they ſhould conſent therein, and withdraw our Militia from thence, he ſhould not be able to continue maſter in the work, but be neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to retire to Batavia, in hope protection ſhould not there be refuſed him, and thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on beſought in all humility, that they would at no hand forſake, and reduce him to ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, but perform their word given him by ſolemn Contract. And how ſhould the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlandiſh Companie be officious to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admiſſion, ſeeing the Engliſh Company in their writings do ſo ſcandalouſly decipher him, as namely, <hi>that he hath with the approbation of all the world acted againſt the English Nation as an Enemie, ſo unthanckful, ſo barbarous, with ſuch antipathie from their Blood, without any the leaſt reaſon or provocation: that his Majeſty of Great Brittain without injurie to his honour, may not reſt till he have ſecured himſelf of that City and whole Kingdom, until he have got reparation, and that the ſooner, becauſe he is, according to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33255:27"/>their ſaying, however he bear the title of King nothing elſe but a perfect Slave of Batavia, and a Servant to their will and pleaſure.</hi> High words indeed: alſo it is a wonderful Dilemma of the Engliſh Companie, to wit, if the Old King of Bantam have any right to Bantam, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendencies thereof, then the concluſion is moſt ſolid, that the ſame is devolved upon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed King of Great Brittain, of happy Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: And if the right appertains to the young King, as the Hollanders affirm, then he hath acted by the approbation of the whole World, againſt the Subjects of his ſaid Maj. as an enemie, &amp; according to what they have deciphred him.</p>
                        <p>Concerning the firſt member of this Dilem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, being it is evident, that the Old King of Bantam having given over his Kingdom to his Eldeſt Son the preſent inheritor thereof, he now cannot afterward give it to another: the concluſion that follows hence is directly againſt the Engliſh Company. What concerns the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of the Dilemma, if it be the young King to whom this right doth belong, and and that it be true, that he had acted againſt the Engliſh as an enemy ungrateful, barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and with antipathie to their blood, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt provocation, as indeed may be drawn, but nevertheleſs not to juſtifie the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Engliſh Company againſt them of Holland, neither can any thing therefrom be concluded againſt the preſent King of Bantam, in caſe he hath juſtly, as he affirmeth, teſtifyed
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:33255:28"/>his diſpleaſure againſt the Engliſh: But in the mean while we cannot let paſs, without ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king notice that while they are pleaſed to heap up reproches upon the young King, then they ſay; <hi>he had acted againſt the Subjects of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty as an enemie, ungrateful, barbarous, with an Antipathie of their Blood, without the leaſt provocation,</hi> further, that he is unworthy of alliance with them; but when the buſineſs is, to load the Dutch, and make them the Authors of their expulſion out of Bantam, then they alter their ſtrain, and ſay, <hi>that they could not ſo much as obſerve neither in the words or geſture of the King the leaſt thing manifeſting any diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure againſt the English, or that he had a deſign to make them depart out of his Connirie.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Here, they name the preſent King a <hi>Slave of the Netherlandish Companie,</hi> and in their Reply they ſay, that <hi>the Old King, when he ſate on his Throne, would willingly have been a Slave of the King of England, and thereof would have made his triumph.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>In their Reply they give the mentioned King the name of a <hi>pauvre Idiot,</hi> a vile per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>une Chetive Creature,</hi> &amp;c. And in their let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they wrote to him in March 1683. they ſtyl him a <hi>wiſe King,</hi> to whom they ſay, they will ſend a perſon with the Title of <hi>Envoy</hi> or <hi>Extraordinary Ambaſſador,</hi> with full power to conclude an everduring League and Alliance with him.</p>
                        <p>The ſame Title the King of Great Brittain
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:33255:28"/>giveth him in his fore mentioned Letter, ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him a <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>righteouſs Prince.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>On the contraire, the English Companie in their Triplick, call him <hi>a Murtherer,</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temner of the publick faith.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And how odiouſly the Engliſh Companie in their foreſaid Letter (annexing alſo, what they wrote to Pangoran Diepa Penerat, Chief Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of State) have deciphred the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh Companie, and in what eſteem we were alreadie with them, even before the Warr of Bantam was kindled, the Dutch Companie will referre to the judgment of the Reader.</p>
                        <p>It hath already been mentioned, that the Engliſh Companie in their foreſaid Demand did pretend, beſides the calling back of the Dutch Troopes, the deliverie alſo of the whole Citie and Caſtle of Bantam, or elſe as they ſaid they would not make their reſidence there again.</p>
                        <p>But beſides that the English Commiſſaries, who were to decide the differences, did as hath been ſaid, Judge, that this their demand, as altogether ungrounded and unreaſonable, ought to be denyed, ſo it is a thing that doth ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refute it ſelf.</p>
                        <p>For before the Warr of Bantam the Engliſh Companie had nothing there but a Lodge and ſimple Reſidence, without the leaſt Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial right: The King after he had triumphed over his Enemies, knowing that they had afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all manner of aſſiſtance to them, and not being
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:33255:29"/>at reſt as fearing their future miſcarriage, and eſpecially in this juncture of time, while he was yet ſurroundred of Enemies, cauſes them to diſlodge: Hereupon now the English Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie comes and demands the deliverie of the whole City and Caſtle, having had nothing there, but as hath been ſaid, a Lodge for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and this they will have from the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlandish Companie, who have no right at all to diſpoſe thereof, except they chaſe away the King that now is, out of Bantam, for to put it into the hands of the English, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they could make it out, and to be agreable to juſtice, that the Dutch Companie ſhould threaten the preſent King to abandon and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver him over to the will and mercie of his Enemies, by remouving of their Troopes out of his Citie, whereas we are bound by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract to maintain and protect him, ſhould now falter in our word, and falſelie our truſt, a thing which may nor ought to be required of us.</p>
                        <p>But it is ſaid, that the Dutch Companies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in this, is to monopoliſe all the trade of Pepper, and get it to themſelves wholie, and to this they ad, that ſeeing the Netherlandish Companie having beſides the trade of Cloves, Nutmegs, Mace and cinnamon, al this would make them able to maintain a fleet to withſtand the mightieſt King in Europe.</p>
                        <p>But beſides that there are ſo many other great countries in the Indies, where Pepper may be
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:33255:29"/>had, and to which the Engliſh Companie have acces as wel as the Dutch, and that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, the Netherlandish Company ſhould get them all under their power &amp; command, it ought to be called to mind, that when we were in trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie here with Sr. John Chardin, that we prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the Pepper-trade in Common to the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Companie, and that by the Contract which ſhould be made with the King the half ſhould be allotted them, of which an article was at that time made, and preſented in writing, but by the ſaid Sr. John Chardin rejected, ſo far was it from the Dutch Companies intention to deſign the ſame, as its malitiously laid to their charge, and not only as to the Pepper-trade, but they add alſo in their Triplick, that the aim of the Dutch Company by this their Reſidence at Bantam, was beſides the Pepper to engroſſe, to their ineſtimable profit, the Linnen-Trade alſo: Whereas on the contrary the Dutch Companie in their foreſaid propoſals to Sr. John Chardin, beſide the Pepper did admit them to the half of all other Wares, including the Linnen, which they alſo refuſed, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding in their ſaid Reply they further ſay, that al the endeavour of the Dutch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie was whether by right or wrong to keep things in the ſtate to which they had brought them.</p>
                        <p>The English Company had firſt ſet in their Demand they gave in, that by our reſidence at Bantam we had made the Pepper-Trade more
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:33255:30"/>difficult to them, but in their forenamed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply they ſay, that we made way to Monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſe the whole, ſo far may men be blinded by paſſion.</p>
                        <p>To what the English Companie doe further depoſe in their foreſaid Demand, viz. that thoſe in pay, of the Dutch Companie, had upon the coaſt of Mallabar aſſaulted their Men, given fire on them, and this alſo to deprive them of the remainder of the Trade in Pepper they as yet had there: The Dutch could have wiſhed, they had more clearly declared themſelves as to the place where, the foreſaid Coaſt laying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longſt the Sea the ſpace of an hundred miles, as alſo to the year and time when, together to what Ship or Barck and upon what occaſion: as on their part the Netherlandish Companie is readie the ſhew after what manner they delt with our Men upon the Weſt Coaſt of Suma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra, to wit the English Fregat .... in Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember 1683 being upon the Coaſt before Ayer Bangi, and ſending out his Chaloup with about fourtie armed Souldiers againſt our men ſitting in a Boat, ſhooting once and again with Bullets: As the Ships the Societie, the Praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, the Eagel and Bercklie Caſtle, who at their return homeward from Bantam, Corman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del and Bengale, in Iuly and the following Months of the year 1681. overwintering at the Iſland Mauritius, committed no ſmall inſolences and miſchiefs, eſpecially they of the Praeſident, and Eagel, robbing and carrying away all what
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:33255:30"/>they found, notwithſtanding all the complaints and proteſtations made by the people of the Dutch Companie, of which we have authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick evidences in hand to ſhew.</p>
                        <p>We paſs by, that the Engliſh for ſo many years have made it their conſtant work, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch our men at Bengale, on the Coaſt of Cormandel, at Bantam, and elſewhere, to draw them out of our ſervice, to ſerve them on their Ships homeward, (being weakly mand) againſt the proteſtations made from time to time, as is to be ſhewn by evidences in hands of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlandish Companie: That the English Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie is entended, as themſelves have divulged, to ſet down and build a Fortreſſe on Priamang, ſeated on the Weſt Coaſt of Sumatra (a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie under the command of the Dutch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and where they have a Fort lying) which by the firſt Letters that come, we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to hear that it is already effected, they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſent to that end divers Ships, with Men, Materials, and warlike furniture: the miſchief that hence will enſue, may eaſilie be geſſed at.</p>
                        <p>It is a thing inconceivable, how they dare publiſh to the world, that the Dutch Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie by a contract made with them of Macaſſer November Anno 1667, and as they ſay, printed at Batavia, by which the English Nation was ſecluded from Commerce in that Countrie, and of which after the expiration of eighteen years, they make complaints in their writings: whereas ſince that time two ſolemn Treatiſes have been made betwixt England and this State,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:33255:31"/>beſide the forenamed agreement of the year 167<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, by which all pretences and actions what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, which might have been againſt each other, were nullifyed as if they never had bin, and although this ſhould not be urged, the Dutch Compagnie is ready to juſtifie what they did, by holding forth to the world their right in making ſuch kind of Contracts: But what in this caſe falls into ſpecial conſideration, is, that the foreſaid Contracts made by the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlandiſh Companie, was during the Warr with England, or before the peace concluded anno 1667. was, or could be known in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, or at Macaſſar.</p>
                        <p>So then although all were true what is publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in a certain writing, and by Mr. Skelton, Envoy Extraordinarie, annexed to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Memorial, preſented to your Puiſ. High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, that we had violently ſeaſed on the Factors of the Engliſh Company, carried them away priſonners to Batavia, and then ſpoiled their Houſes (although the Companie, upon their Faith and Credit, are ignorant hereof) what could this any way help the Engliſh, or why ſhould they thus exclaime about it? Hath not England about this verie time taken by force New-Netherland from our Weſt-Indie Companie, &amp; can the Dutch Weſt-Indie Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie frame an action or pretence hereon? With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, No.</p>
                        <p>The English Companie finding themſelves deſtitute of neceſſarie proofs to make good
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:33255:31"/>the matter of Fact, they charge the Dutch Companie with, which nevertheleſs can only ſerve as the foundation of what they urge, as alſo being convinced of the unanſwerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation made by the Dutch Companie, with moſt evident demonſtration of the ungrounded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the aſſertions of the English Companie, they betake themſelves in their Reply to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proches, calumniating the Dutch Companie in the conduct of their affaires after ſo odious a manner, and in ſuch extravagant termes, as muſt needs make all men aſtoniſhed, how peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of honour and underſtanding ſhould ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get themſelves, yea ſo far as that the Engliſh Commiſſaries themſelves in the conference with the Commiſſaries who on our ſide were, to decide the buſineſs, were conſtrained to abhor and manifeſt their diſcontent thereof: And although the Dutch wanted no matter to convince the English Companie of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable injurie, and to diſabuſe the World of ſo many untruths falsly imputed to them, yet they judged it better to abſtain and with a modeſt ſilence to paſs it by, then enter into further conteſt, and make the rupture of the Friendſhip (which is ſo neceſſary between both the Companies) yet greater, and the wound incurable.</p>
                        <p>The Demand the Dutch Company made by reconvention, conſiſted herein, that they at the earneſt requeſt of the English Companie had lent or accommodated them with four Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:33255:32"/>for the tranſport of their perſons, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſes and effects from Bantam to Batavia, under promiſe by writing to pay the Dutch Companie for the fraight, theſe Ships they kept ſome moneths, making uſe of them in ſtead of Magaſins, and for preſervation of their wares and effects, to the great prejudice of the Dutch Companie, who ſtood in verie great need of them, in reſpect of their traffick, but could not get them again what meanes and inſinuations ſoever they uſed, till ſome months after.</p>
                        <list>
                           <head>The foreſaid Ships were,</head>
                           <item>Europa, big 600. laſt.</item>
                           <item>New Middleborow, big 500. laſt.</item>
                           <item>Delfshaven, 450. laſt.</item>
                           <item>'t Wout, 100. laſt.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The fraight of which amounted to the ſumme of 13900. L. ſtarl.</p>
                        <p>It remains that we ſpeak a word or two of what happened before Gamron in the Gulph of Perſia, over which alſo the English Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie make their complaints, firſt, in a certain Article in their Triplick, and afterward by that writing which the foreſaid Mr. Skelton Extraordinarie Envoy, annexed to the foreſaid Memorial by him preſented the .. of May laſt to your Puiſ. Highneſſes, of which men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was made in the beginning: This Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle containes firſt complaints againſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of the Fleet, which lately the Dutch Company had in the Gulph of Perſia with
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:33255:32"/>which they entended, as they ſay, to ſhut or lock up all the Havens of that great Kingdom.</p>
                        <p>And the ſaid Memorial did further make like complaints that the foreſaid Fleet conducted by Reynier Kaſembroot, with violence ſhould have hindred John Goldsborough Maſter of an Engliſh Companies Ship called the Marchant of Bengale, from onlading the ſaid Ship with Boats, thereby detaintng and diſturbing him in all their traffick and buſineſs: but after exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination this complaint wil be found as ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, as any of the other.</p>
                        <p>The caſe is this, that the Netherlandiſh Companie time out of mind, having a Comp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toir or Lodge, together with their Traffick at Gamron, and other places in the Kingdom of Perſia, by vertue of an agreement made with the King, and of Priviledges granted unto them, the Perſians in many points ſet themſelves in oppoſition againſt them, offring them many outragious and unjuſt dealings, and foraſmuch as no reparation or redres in the leaſt could be obtained by any requeſts made, although ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with extraordinarie and coſtlie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, at laſt it burſt forth into deeds, for to repair the injurie don, and this is the Fleet of Ships, which the Dutch Companie for this end had in the foreſaid Gulph, with which they took from the Perſians the Jland Kiſmus with the Caſtle in the ſaid Gulph, not far diſtant from Ormus or Gamron, not for to keep, for it could not have been ſerviceable to us, but with
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:33255:33"/>intollerable charge, onely it was don to induce and neceſſitate the Perſians to condeſcend to reaſon, which it alſo effected, whereupon the Netherlandiſh Companie reſtored the I land and the Caſtle to the Perſians again.</p>
                        <p>What then concerns the firſt complaint, that with that Fleet the Netherlandiſh Companie ſought to ſhut up all the Havens in Perſia, the Netherlandiſh Companie is neceſſitated to ſay, that it is verie ſtrange to them, that they ſhould ſo wrongfully and malitiouſly miſconſter the good intention of the Netherlandiſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
                        <p>Hath the Dutch Company with that Fleet of Ships done them the leaſt wrong or hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, as to what concerns their coming or departing in or from the ſaid Havens? yea even during the time that the Netherlandiſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie lay with the whole Fleet before Gamron? Have not the Engliſh ſayled in and out, as they pleaſed? They cannot but ſay, yea.</p>
                        <p>What reaſon had they then to judge ſo mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly of their deſign.</p>
                        <p>But in the foreſaid Triplick it is ſaid, that the Netherlandiſh Company intended indeed to ſet on foot and effect it, in caſe the Engliſh had not by hap appeared there with a greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Ships, not to be hindred or forced by the Netherlanders.</p>
                        <p>But before they were arrived there with any number of Ships together, did not the foreſaid Fleet and the ſaid Kaſembroot let their ſingle
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:33255:33"/>Ships go in and out freely and unmoleſted, yea even their Boats and Chalops: and with them alſo their Ship Williamſon loden with Goods fraited for and belonging to the Perſians? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they cannot deny it.</p>
                        <p>And what concerns this great number of Ships, which they ſay they afterward had there, if compared with the number, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the greatneſs of the Netherlandish Ships, all mounted, mand, and in gallant equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page for Warr, they were ſtrong enuff, had they had order, to have kept them out of Gam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron.</p>
                        <p>The Netherlandish Fleet lay a year and ſome months before Gamron, and the Engliſh were but a ſmall time with their foreſaid number of Ships there, whereas before and after there came other, yea ſingle Ships, to and fro, and yet according to their own confeſſion no ſtop or hinderance was don to any of them, ſave on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Ship called the Marchant of Bengale before mentioned, and of which ſhall be further ſpoken by and by.</p>
                        <p>From whence then is it evinced, that the Dutch Company had ſuch a deſign, or what proofs do they bring, to juſtifie what they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in their foreſaid Reply? Not one only word.</p>
                        <p>But to ſay how the caſe ſtands, the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landish Companie undertakes to ſhew, that the ſaid Kaſembroot, commanding the ſaid Fleet in Chief in the Gulph of Perſia, did all
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:33255:34"/>the time of his abode there, by expreſs order and command, forbid, that no let or hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſhould in the leaſt be offered to the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Ships in their navigation and traffick in that Kingdom.</p>
                        <p>And, that the Dutch Companies manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might be rendred the more ſuſpected and odious, they conclude thus in their Triplick, theſe are the meanes which the Dutch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie uſeth, for to get great advantages upon the Indian Princes, yea have thereby con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained that great and mightie King of Perſia himſelf to ſubſcribe ſuch Articles, as they would, that he might have his Havens again open and free.</p>
                        <p>But beſides that the Netherlandish Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie hath not, by all thoſe exceſſive charges, covenanted or acquired any greater priviledges or advantages then they alwayes formerly have had in the Kingdom, except onely a diſcharge from taking yearly a quantity of Silk at a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain price, (at leaſt ſo far as concerns the laſt) according to the advice, which the Dutch Companie lately received concerning the ſame.</p>
                        <p>And in caſe the great Princes of the Indies, and the King of Perſia himſelf were ſo eaſily to be forced by ſuch a Fleet as the Dutch Companie had there, we have reaſon to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, why the English Companie did not make uſe of that occaſion, namely when they had preſent ſuch a Fleet as they boaſt of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:33255:34"/>Gamron, for to recover of the Perſians payment of the Tol or Cuſtom of Ormus or Gamron, which they ſay was ſo truely due unto them, but unjuſtly detained by the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, at leaſt as to the greater part thereof, and which in the year 1654. they demanded, as to the half thereof, amounting to many hundred thouſand gilders, of the Netherlandish Companie, to wit, of the Goods which the ſaid Dutch Company until that time had brought and negotiated there, but was then by Committies on both parts denyed to be due to them, and they remitted to the Perſians them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, where they ſo often importuned them by their complaints, yea even to the threatning of them, but neverthleſs could never obtain any ſatisfaction: would they not in all that time, wherein theſe pretences have ſince en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed to ſuch vaſt ſums, if it had bin to be acquired with ſuch facility, have uſed theſe wayes and meanes? Undoubtedly yea.</p>
                        <p>And thereby we may wel judge, what was the Conſtitution of that Fleet they had there, and of which they made ſuch high boaſts.</p>
                        <p>But in caſe they ſhould yet attempt the ſame, could the Netherlandish Company, although much prejudiced thereby in their Traffick, as undoubted would ſo be, could they thereupon lay any action to the charge of the English Company, and make pretences upon them?</p>
                        <pb n="70" facs="tcp:33255:35"/>
                        <p>Surely the Dutch Companie would wiſh, yea, entreat in a friendly way, that if ſuch a thing ſhould be, our Ships might have the like uſage, as the Dutch Companie did ſhew to the English.</p>
                        <p>As to the ſecond complaint, namely the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance occaſioned to the Ship the Marchant of Bengale in her unloding, by detaining and diſturbing them in their Traffick and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings.</p>
                        <p>Thus ſtands the caſe: The Dutch Company, as hath been ſaid, having War with the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, or being as they ſay, <hi>in ſtatu belli,</hi> and laying with their Fleet before Gamron, there came tyding from Land, that there was an intent to bord our Fleet by fire Ships, and ſo cauſe us to leave the rode; whereupon we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ceaſe on all the Perſian Boats we could get, and make them faſt behind our Ships: the foreſaid English Ship laying in the midſt of our Fleet, and making preparation to unlode in Perſian Boats, the ſaid Kaſembroot deſired them to be pleaſed to deſiſt, and not to make uſe of Perſian Boats, eſpecially they being accuſtomed to take in their loding in the night time to be verie earlie at land to unlode, we offring them al the Boats of our Ships to aſſiſt them, that we might be certain, that they under the cloack of coming to the foreſaid Ship, with their Fireſhips, and paſſing by our watch, might not before we were aware, fal upon us; but they of the foreſaid Ship re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:33255:35"/>our proffer, there came among our Fleet a Perſian Boat, mand with ten or twelve Perſian Rowers and one English Mariner, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by him two caſes with Roſewater, which the ſaid Kaſembroot cauſed to be brought into his Ship: the English Interpreter preſently there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon making his complaint, the former proffer of our Boats was renieuwed, and at his going away bid to take with him the two caſes of Roſewater, which he refuſing, they were put into his Boat, and ſo he departed.</p>
                        <p>This being the true hiſtorie, we demand, what herein was don amiſſe by the Dutch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, to cauſe the English to make ſuch cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous complaints about it? Or whither if any hinderance came thereby to the English (for damage they had none) they brought it not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their own heads?</p>
                        <p>The goods they accuſe us to have taken out of the Perſian boat (which nevertheleſſe they themſelves confeſſe were agayn reſtored, and put into the boat where the Engliſh interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was) They aggravate, for to make them, in all apearance, to ſeem of great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; were onely the foreſaid two Caſes of Roſewater.</p>
                        <p>In the Contra-Proteſt, the foreſaid Kaſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broot hath made agaynſt the Proteſt of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh (and to which they appeal) the whole carriage of the buſineſſe is nakedly and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made to appeare, for which reaſon they alſo thought good, as the ſaid Extraordinarie
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:33255:36"/>Envoy annexed the ſaid Proteſt of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh to his foreſaid Memorial, here withal alſo to deliver over this Contra-Proteſt.</p>
                        <p>Thereby more plainly to ſhew: firſt, the Proffer we made of our boats for their ſervice to unlode their ſaid ſhip, partly to take away the hinderance they Complayned of, and on the other hand to prevent the miſchief, which by the going to and fro of the enemies boats, (which they might have pretended to be don only in the name and by the order of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh) could have befallen our fleet.</p>
                        <p>Again, that the goods taken out the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian Boat, but again reſtored, were nothing but the ſaid Caſes of Roſewater.</p>
                        <p>And thirdly, that the Engliſh, during our diſſention with the Perſians, did al what they could to incenſe them agaynſt us by Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and falshoods, which alſo did remarke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably retard and ſet back our Buſineſſe at Court, to the great loſſe and detriment of the Dutch Companie.</p>
                        <p>Eſpetially by the promiſes they made the Perſians with ſix ſhips to chaſe us from the Rode of Gamron, and out of the Fort of Kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, whenas nevertheleſſe our ſaid fleet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted of nine ſhips, and of which the Dutch Companie expects due information at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of our fleet.</p>
                        <p>And hereby the directors of the Netherlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dish Companie hope they have Satiſfied the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of your Puiſſant Highneſſes, having mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:33255:36"/>on the one hand the Notorious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groundedneſſe of all the Complaints brought in by the Engliſh, and on the otherhand the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie of the Netherlandiſh Companie in theſe matters: and that thereby your Puiſſant High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes wil the more be incited, to appeare for the Dutch Companie in ſo righteous a cauſe, and to Protect them agaynſt al and Everie one, that ſhal endeavor for this any wayes to moleſt or injurie them, which by theſe preſents we moſt humbly requeſt; having judged that the importance of the Cauſe, and the multiplicitie of enormous acts where with the Netherlandish Companie is Loaden, and that we might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute al theſe things in a due manner, as alſo giue pour Puiſſant Highneſſes a Grounded infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, did require this our Large Exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of things, and which in all humilitie we beg may not be unacceptable to your Puiſſant Highneſſes.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Was ſubcribed:, P. VAN DAM.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:33255:37"/>
                     <head>Contra Proteſt to the ungroun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded agrievances of the English Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents DANIEL EDWARDS and FRANCIS SNAPE, both in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Honorable Engliſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie here in Perſia.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>WE received yeſternight the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt you ſent, and greatly wonder at the aggrierances you make about a Perſian bark paſſing through our fleet, and for ſome time detained by us, which you affirm to have hired for to unlade the Merchandiſes, of the ſhip called the Merchant of Bengale, to which we anſwer, that it can not be unknown to you that we have more then a year ſecured this Rode and Gulph with eight or nine ſhips, and notwithſtanding that our Commiſſioners for the compounding of the differences are at preſent at the court of Perſia, yet our men ſome few dayes agoe have in a moſt hoſtile man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner bin driven from land, our flag taken down, and we as is noyſed by them of Gamron, threatned to be aſſaulted here in the Rode by a number of barcks, manned with Perſian Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia, ſo that nature treacheth us to be upon our watch, and we thereuppon thought it neceſſarie
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:33255:37"/>to ſeaſe all the Perſian boats, yet without the leaſt thought of doeing any let or hinderance to you, as your ſelves know that in the unla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the ſhip Williamſon was not don, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ſaid ſhip both going and comming was fraighted with Perſian goods, but on the contrarie the day before yeſterday, when we ſtopt the Perſian Barq, which would have paſſed our fleet, we proffered your Truchman David all our own boats for to help the ſaid ſhip to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lade, both becauſe we would not hinder them in their affaires, as alſo to ſecure our own ſhips from the threatned miſchiefs, (which by the ſwarving of the Enemies boats, pretending to com in the name and by the order of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish) might have befallen us. But it ſeemeth, you were rather prone thus unjuſtly to accuſe us, that we ſhould have detained your goods (which were onely the two caſes of Roſewater) then to embrace the kinde proffer of our Boats: The ſaid, David your Truchman tooke the two Caſes into the ſcute wherin he came from land, at the ſame time the the barck came abord to us, and himſelf caried them away with him: And for as much as it ſeemeth to be your wonted manner, by intricate and practiſed inſertions to render things obſcure, this your ungrounded accuſations are not ſtrange unto us, as having ſince this expedition, with much patience born all the calumnious reproches, wherewith you have a long time ſought to make us odious to the Perſian Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:33255:38"/>to retard our agreement with them, Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially promiſing them, to make us, with ſix of your ſhips, to retire out of this Rode, and out of Kiſmus, of al which we have ſuffitient proofs to ſhew, and withal to make it appeare, we had not given you the leaſt reaſon or provocation thereto: Al which hath bin to the apparent dammage of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, and beſides this yee ſeek alſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain us to let our Enemies barcks to pas and repas our fleet: Wherefore in the name of the Netherlandish Eaſt-Indie Companie we doe Proteſt we are innocent of al the blood, ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, loſſes and inconveniences which ſhall reſult from thence, on the one or other hand: Given in our ſhip, the Blaw-Hulck laying in the Rode before Gamron.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Was ſigned, <hi>R: Kaſembroot. W: Licochton. J: V: Ackerſdijck, and W: van Bulleſtraten.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:33255:38"/>
                     <head>Contra-Proteſt againſt John Golds-bourough, Maſter of the Ship called the Bengale Marchant.</head>
                     <p>THe firſt of June Old ſtile was delivered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, by them thereunto appointed, your Proteſt, which having conſidered, we do find in it many things are miſtaken, and by you preſſed contrary to trueth, and therefore judge it unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, to give any anſwer thereunto, then what was don by our Inſinuaion and Proteſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered over the thirteenth and fourteenth of May N. S. to the Engliſh Reſidents Daniel Edwards and Francis Snape, of which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with a Copie is inſerted, and wherein the true ſtate of things is fully conteined, and to which therefore we referre our ſelves: however we profeſs to be blameleſs, that you by misſailing to ſhore came to touch ground once &amp; again with your Ship, as not being to be imputed to us, but your own unadviſedneſs: Beſides we did never forbid or withſtand, that any Barcks ſhould come to you to fetch Ballaſt, and is therefore the fault of the Perſians, to whom the loſſe of time you ſay, to have bin hindred by it, is alſo to be imputed and not to us, and withall would let you know, we are not ſuch unqualifyed perſons as you are pleaſed to terme us, which rather may be imputed to you, as ſufficiently appeares by your unreaſonable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:33255:39"/>and therefore are not any whit troubled, in caſe any diſpute doe ariſe thereabout between you and our Company, to be able, as having juſtice and truth on our ſide, to anſwer what hath bin don: Wherefore we Proteſt in the name and on behalf of the Netherlandish Eaſt-Indie Company, againſt you, John Golds-borough, Maſter of the Ship called the Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale Marchant, and againſt all other, whoever they be or whom it may concern, that we are blameleſs, and not bound to make ſatisfaction of your ungrounded pretences, or what any one may unjuſtly lay to our charge. Given in our Ship the Blaw Hulck, laying in the Rode before Gamron the 19. June 1685. S. N.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>There ſtood underneath and was ſigned <hi>Reynier Kaſembroot,</hi> and <hi>Wouter van Bulleſtraten,</hi> In the Margin, Delivered by us underwritten, And was ſigned, <hi>Andries van der Linden,</hi> and <hi>Jacob Stuyt.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="extract">
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:33255:39"/>
                     <head>EXTRACT out the Regiſter of the Reſolutions of the High and Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Lords the States General of the United Provinces.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Thurſday the</hi> 18. <hi>Julie,</hi> 1686.</date>
                     </opener>
                     <p>IT being deliberated by Reſumption upon the Memorial delivered up by the Directors of the Eaſt-Indie Company of theſe Countries the 22. of June paſt unto their Puiſſant High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, containing the conſequents, and for ſatisfaction to their Puiſſ. Highneſſes Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the 31. May paſt their Information upon the Memorial of Mr. Skelton Envoy Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary of his Royal Majeſty of Great Brittain to this State, delivred up the ſecond of the ſaid Month to their Puiſſ. Highneſſes, touching the affaires of Bantam, it is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood and found meet by theſe, to requeſt and give Commiſſion to the Lords van Els and the other Deputies of their Puiſſant Highneſſes for Outlandiſh affaires, to ſignifie to Mr. Skel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Envoy Extraordinary, that the differences concerning what hath paſt at Bantam in the year 1682. being ariſen to the State they are now fallen to his ſaid Majeſty and their Puiſſ Highneſſes, They are prepared and readie to tread into a Conference and treatie thereof, with the ſaid Mr. Skelton, ſo he be authoriſed
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:33255:40"/>thereto in behalf of his Majeſty, or elſe with them, whom his ſaid Majeſty ſhall be pleaſed to authoriſe thereto, and in that Conference and Treatie to ſhew, that their Puiſſ. High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes have no other meaning and intention, then to preſerve and cultivate with his ſaid Majeſty and Subjects an entire amity, and that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not to do any wrong unto his Majeſties Subjects. Hereunder ſtood, Agreeth, with the foreſaid Regiſter, Was ſubſcribed</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>H. FAGEL.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="extract">
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:33255:40"/>
                     <head>EXTRACT Out of the Regiſter of the Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of the High and Mightie Lords the States General of the United Provinces.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Tweſday</hi> 1. <hi>July</hi> 1687.</date>
                     </opener>
                     <argument>
                        <p>Was read at the Aſſembly the Memorial of the Marquis of Albiville, Extraordinarie Envoy of his Majeſty of Great Brittain, requiring reparation for what paſſed at Bantam, according to what is here inſerted word for word.</p>
                     </argument>
                     <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <opener>
                              <salute>High and Mightie Lords,</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>AS there is nothing which may contribute more efficaciouſly to the maintenance and eſtabiſhment of Leagues and Alliances made between Kings and States, then a Juſt and and prompt reparation of the Wrong, Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Loſſes, which the Subjects of one receive from the other.</p>
                           <p>Therefore the Marquis of Albiville, Envoy Extraordinary of the King of Great Brittain, findeth himſelf commanded by the Order of the King his Maſter to put your Highneſſes in remembrance of the moſt conſiderable loſſes, enormous Iniuries, and the Honour of his
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33255:41"/>Subjects moſt ſenſiblie wounded by the ſurrep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious, ungodly and inſupportable proceeding of the Eaſt-Indie Companie of this State at Bantam, and to require without further delay an entire Satisfaction proportionable to the Enormitie of the attempt, and to the Loſſes which the Subjects of his ſaid Majeſty have ſuffered. Given at the Hague the 30. June in the year 1687.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Signed, <hi>The Marquis of Albiville.</hi>
                              </signed>
                           </closer>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                     <p>Which being deliberated upon, it is found good and underſtood, that a Copie of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Memorial ſhall be put into the hands of the Lords Everwyn and other their Puiſſ. High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes Deputies for the affaires of the Eaſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die Companie, to viſit and examin the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners of the Directors of the ſaid Company thereof to heare, as alſo to take the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and moſt wiſe Adviſe of his Highneſſe the Prince of Orange, and to make report of the whole to the Aſſemblie here, and that forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with an Extract of this their Puiſſ. Highneſſes Reſolution, and a Cope of the foreſaid Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial ſhall be ſent to the Directors of the ſaid Eaſt-Indie Companie of the Praeſidial Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber at Amſterdam, and therewith written to them, that againſt this day fortnight, which ſhall be the 15. of the preſent Moneth, they
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:33255:41"/>ſend hither ſom Commiſſioners wel inſtruct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d upon the foreſaid ſubject, that ſo the next d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> earlie in the morning the ſaid buſineſs may be taken in hand.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Was paragraphed <hi>B. van Schelting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>.</hi> Lower ſtood, Agreeth with the foreſaid Regiſter. Was ſigned, <hi>H. Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="extract">
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:33255:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <head>EXTRACT out of the Regiſter of the Reſolutions of the High and Mightie Lords the States General of the United Netherland.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Weddenſday</hi> 23. <hi>July</hi> 168<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</date>
                     </opener>
                     <p>WAs heard the report or the Lords Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolt bolt and other their Puiſſ. Highneſſes De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties for Outlandiſh affaires, having in order and to ſatisfying of their Reſolution, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionated the 1. of this preſent, viſited and examined the Memorial of the Marquis of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biville Envoy Extraordinary of his Majeſtie of Great Brittain to this State, by which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth reparation for what is paſſed at Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, more largely mentioned in the ſaid Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial and in the Brief notes of this preſent: upon which having deliberated, is found good and underſtood, that to the ſaid Marquis of Albeville for anſwer to the ſaid Memorial ſhall be inſinuated, that their Puiſſ. Highneſſes by their Reſolution 18. July of the year paſt 1686. have declared to Mr. Skelton, as then his Majeſties Envoy Extraordinary to this State, that the differences about what paſſed at Bantam in Juin 1682, being ariſen to the State that they were devolved to his ſaid Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and their Puiſſ. Highneſſes, they are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared and readie to enter into a Conference
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:33255:42"/>and treatie thereabout with the fore mentioned Mr. Skelton, if that he on the part of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty be authoriſed thereunto, or otherwiſe with ſuch as his ſaid Majeſtie ſhould be pleaſed to authoriſe, and in that Conference and Treatie to ſhew that their Puiſſ. Highneſſes have no other meaning nor intention, then to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and cultivate with the ſaid Majeſtie and his Subjects an entire amitie, and that they doe not pretend to doe any wrong to his Majeſties Subjects; and that therefore their Puiſſ. High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes could not have expected otherwiſe, from the juſtice of His Majeſtie, but that the ſaid Conference ſhould have been ſet on foot, and ſome perſon thereunto authoriſed: and now as yet they adhere to reniew the foreſaid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, and ſay, that they ſtill are readie to enter into Conference and treatie about the foreſaid Differences with the ſaid Marquis of Albiville, in caſe he on the part of his Majeſty be authoriſed thereto, or otherwiſe with ſuch, as his Majeſtie ſhall be pleaſed to authoriſe, &amp; in thoſe Conferences and Treatiſes to ſhew, that they have no other meaning nor intention then to preſerve and cultivate with his Majeſty and Subjects an entire Friendſhip, and pretend not to do or ſuffer any wrong be don unto His Majeſties Subjects, and therefore they cannot conceive or apprehend what the foreſaid Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial, and the terms in which it is couched, would have, or ſignifie; And an Extract of this their Puiſſ. Highneſſes Reſolution ſhall by the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:33255:43"/>Agent Sprouſſen be delivered into the hands or the Marquis of Albiville, to ſerve for his Information, thereof to make uſe ſo and where it ſhall be thought fit; and alſo an Extract of this their Puiſſ. Highneſſes Reſolution ſhall be ſent to the Lord Citters, their Puiſſ. High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes Ambaſſador at the Court of His Majeſty the King of Great Brittain, to be ſubſervient unto his Information.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Was paragraphed, <hi>Francis Verbelt.</hi> Underneath ſtood, Accordeth with the foreſaid Regiſter, Signed, H. FAGEL</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="extract">
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:33255:43"/>
                     <head>EXTRACT out of the Regiſter of the Reſolutions of the High and Mightie Lords the States General of the United Netherlands.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Friday the</hi> 1. <hi>Auguſti</hi> 1687.</date>
                     </opener>
                     <argument>
                        <p>WAs read at the Aſſemblie the Memorial of the Marquis of Albiville Envoy Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie of his Majeſtie of Great Brittain to this ſtate, together with an Appendix Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining complaints agaynſt the Eaſt-Indie Companie of theſe countries, as to what ſhould have bin attempted at Metocapatans and at Baktancapas according to the ſaid Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial, and the appendix inſerted here by, from word to word,</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Fiat inſertio:</hi>
                        </p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>Whereupon being deliberated was found good and underſtond that a Copie of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Memorial and appendix ſhal be ſent to the Directors of the Eaſt-Indie Companie of the Praſidial Chamber of Amſterdam, for to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe an information thereupon to their Puiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Highneſſes, and nevertheles alſo a Copie and appendix thereof ſhal delivered into the hands of the Lords Verbolt and other their
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33255:44"/>Puiſſant Highneſſes Deputies for outlandish affaires, to reviſe, Examin and make report of the whole here at the Aſſemblie:</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Was paragraphed, <hi>John vander Bergh,</hi> vt, Underneah ſtood, agreeth with the foreſaid Regiſter, <hi>Was ſigned</hi> H. FAGEL</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:33255:44"/>
                     <head>Memorial of the Marquis of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biville Exhibited the 1. Auguſt 1687.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>High and Mightie Lords,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>THe Marquis of Abbiville Envoy Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie of the King of Great Brittain hath received niew orders from the King his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, to ſignifie to your Lordſhips the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of nieu injuſtices and violences offred by your Companie of the Eaſt-Indies at Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chapatans and Batancapas, as they ſhal ſee by the adjoyned writing containing the Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars thereof.</p>
                     <p>And as his Majeſtie findeth himſelft informed of the anſwere of your Highneſſes the 23 of the month paſt unto the preceding Memorial of his aboue ſaid Envoy, is willing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that theſe things have bin committed without your knowledge, ſo like wiſe he doth not Doubt, but they are of ill ſavor and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>approved by your Highneſſes, and that he cannot but expect from your juſtice and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the reparation of theſe infractions, and the dammages which the Subjects of his Majeſtie have ſuffered in theſe quarters, His Majeſtie wil willingly alſo be perswaded by the aſſeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances which the ſaid Memorial giveth him that your Highneſſe wil not neglect to ſend
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:33255:45"/>preciſe and Effectual orders, to the end that for the future the like attempt, be no more uſed: as the faireſt meanes to maintain a good intelligence betwixt His Majeſtie and this Commonwealth, to which his Majeſtie, on his part ſhal not fail to contribute allwayes, what in reaſon may be deſired of him. Given at the Hague this 1. Auguſt 1687.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Signed,</hi> Marquis of ALBIVILLE.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="appendix">
                     <head>APPENDIX.</head>
                     <p>THe Engliſh Eaſt-Indie Companie in a Requeſt they preſented to his Majeſty of Great Britain 29. June 1687. ſay, they have had adviſe by divers Ships niewly arrived, of the injuries and violences the Hollanders have exerciſed againſt the Engliſh on the Coaſt of Cormandel, under pretext of having warr with the King of Golcondach.</p>
                     <p>That they made themſelves maſter of Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chalapatam, after the ſame manner they ceaſed Bantam.</p>
                     <p>That they had prohibited the Engliſh eight weeks ago to Traffick there any more, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though, they have had their reſidence and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaſin there eightie or ninetie yeares together, and that the Magaſin was built by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:33255:45"/>and that they bought the verie ground upon which it was erected, as may be ſeen in the writing of the Governor and the Dutch Counſel at Pollicats.</p>
                     <p>That the Hollanders in time of peace did by main force Aſſault the Fort the Engliſh had built at Batancapas, ſeated on the Weſt-Coaſt of Sumatra, to ſecure themſelves the better of the Traffick in Pepper; that in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt they brake and tore in peeces the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villion of his Brittiſh Majeſty where is was ſet up.</p>
                     <p>That they there pillaged the Engliſh.</p>
                     <p>And becauſe it is apparent, the deſign of the Hollanders is to appropriate to themſelves by violence, injuſtice and oppreſſion the whole Trade of the Eaſt-Indies, The ſaid Companie hopeth that his Majeſtie with the firſt will applie ſuch remedies, as may prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the continual invaſions of the Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
                     <p>A Letter of the Holland Companie from Pollicat, written the 13. Auguſt 1686. St. N. to Mr. William Gifford, Praeſident of the Engliſh Companie, and to his Counſel at the Fort St. George.</p>
                     <p>It containes in ſubſtance, that the ſaid Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh Companie hath bin evil treated, ſome years ſince, beyond the Coaſt of Cormandel, as alſo the North Coaſt from Onixa, unto Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chopotam, by the Miniſters of State, and the Governors of the King of Gulcondach.</p>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:33255:46"/>
                     <p>That they often required juſtice, but to no purpoſe, and for to revenge themſelves of theſe injuries, they had ſeaſed Metchopotem 16. July. That for a marck of the Friendſhip they deſire to maintain with the Engliſh Company, they permit them, to embarck in their own Ships out of their Magaſins at Metchepotam the effects the English had there, as alſo to take out in Barcks all the Proviſions and all the Marchandiſes which ſhall com in their Ships to Metchopotam for to put them into their Magaſins, yet upon condition that they ſhall carrie none out of the Citie of Metchopotam, to ſell them to Marchants, or to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the King of Gulcondagh, until the ſaid Company ſhall have ſatisfactions.</p>
                     <p>The ſooner to obtain this ſatisfaction they had reſolved not only to hold the mean while the ſaid Citie in poſſeſſion, but alſo to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent that the English ſhould not ſuffer any da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage during theſe troubles, they though it fit to advertiſe them to bring into their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaſins the effects they had in the Countrie, and that within the ſpace of 6. or 8. weeks, recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from the time the Companie had ſeaſed the ſaid City.</p>
                     <p>That they will alſo have, that the English Company advertiſe theirs of all what they shall cauſe to be brought in, to the end that by the good order they ſhall hold, the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences may be prevented, which otherwiſe might befal the English.</p>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:33255:46"/>
                     <p>Anſwer of Mr. William Gifford Praeſident, and of the Councel of the English Company, dated .... 1686. written to the Hollands Company at Pollicat. It being in ſubſtance: That the English Company are not ignorant of the deſign the Dutch Company now hath in making themſelves Maſters in Metchapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam.</p>
                     <p>That they could wish that the ruinating of the English Commerce were not the main end, the Hollanders now a long time had practiſed theſe tricks: Particularly at Bantam and ſince at Chimatra, but that the Hollanders were as yet to be reſponſable unto them.</p>
                     <p>That they have remarqued that the Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in all their Treaties they make with the Indian Kings and Princes, have endeavoured to exclude their Companie from Traffick in their Countries and Ports.</p>
                     <p>That this deſign is now diſcovered and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in Europe, that their preſumption is to great to impoſer Lawes to the English in ſuch a manner, that now, ſince they are poſſeſſors of Metchapotam they will have the English to comport themſelves as to their commerce there, according to their pleaſurre: But the English are not obliged to follow their order, That the Houſe and the ground upon which their Magaſin is built is an heritage acquired by their own money.</p>
                     <p>That upon theſe grounds they counſel them to act with diſcretion and agreeing to juſtice.</p>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:33255:47"/>
                     <p>That they in the mean while will continue to traffick as formerly, and counſel the Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders not to interrupt them, leaſt they ſhould attract ſad conſequences contrarie to their intereſt.</p>
                     <p>A Letter of Mr. Samuel Pots written to Mr. Clement du Jardin, and to the Council.</p>
                     <div type="part">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Indraponna the</hi> 
                              <date>23. <hi>Sept.</hi> 1686.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>It containes firſt a Relation of the ſtate of ſome of the affaires of the English Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Pots remits them to a certain Paper of 26. July to be informed of the cauſe of his voyage to Batancapas, and why he took with him ſo much of the Companies effects.</p>
                        <p>He gives reaſons, why he did not wayt for orders or command, before he undertook the voyage, that it was, becauſe the two Sons of the Emperor and the Mandarins, had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly preſſed him to haſten the voyage, as much as could be, leſt the Hollanders being advertiſed of the deſign of the English, ſhould ſettle themſelves there before, and ſo the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish be fruſtrated of their entrepriſe.</p>
                        <p>He departed, as he ſaith, from Indraponna 16. July, taking with him forty men Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks and Soldiers, going with them to Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to meet there the two Sons of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror Manuncabbo, who wayted them to go together to Batancapas, being in all 2000.
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:33255:47"/>there to ſettle the Engliſh. That after 5 dayes voyage they arrived with the Emperor and the two Princes: and that the Emperor had bid the Engliſh to ſettle themſelves there.</p>
                        <p>That three dayes before they arrived the Hollanders had ſettled and fortified them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves there upon a Rock on the other ſide of the river, notwithſtanding that the Emperor and the Mandarins had commanded them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, telling them that he had given the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey to the King of Great Brittain to ſet the Engliſh Companie there; and that he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver given permiſſion to the Dutch to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide there.</p>
                        <p>That the ſame day of his arriving at Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancapas the Hollanders had ſent him a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, counſelling him to take good heed of the Malayans, becauſe they complayned that the Engliſh had wronged them by ſetling at Bancola and at Indraponna, places which, they ſayd, had formerly bin given unto them.</p>
                        <p>That at the end of two dayes he ſent them another Proteſt.</p>
                        <p>That the day after his arriving, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror and his two ſons arrived, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves planted the Pavillion of the King of England.</p>
                        <p>That the Hollanders had fortifyed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as much as they could.</p>
                        <p>That during the 3 firſt weeks there was no oppoſition of the one or other part, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Engliſh did often preſſe the Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layans
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:33255:48"/>to fall upon the English.</p>
                        <p>That the Hollanders ſeeing that after all their perſwaſions, the Mallayans would do nothing, forced them to retire further up into the Countrie, about three miles towards the North, with deſign (as the Emperor and his men believed) to waſt the Countrie, the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and eſpecially the City of Batancapas.</p>
                        <p>That to prevent this deſolation the Emperor and his two Sons had drawn back their forces, except 60. or 70. Mallayans, whom they left there for to cover the works.</p>
                        <p>That after the retreat of theſe Troopes the the Hollanders in Batancapas the day after beeing the 23. Auguſt on a Friday and on the Sunday had ſhot with their greateſt Canons at the people as they came to the Market in hope to make them afraid, and no more to ſupply the English, or to bring them any more provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
                        <p>That a Canon-bullet with two points ſtriking a tree neer the Palliſado of the English Fort, burſt aſunder in two pieces.</p>
                        <p>That the day after they had diſpatched Mr. Samuel Worly to the Hollanders to know of them the reaſon wherefore they had ſhot at the Magaſin of the Engliſh and their men, and to tel their commander they would ſend a peece of the Bullet of the King of England, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form him of the affront they had don to his Subjects, but the Commander not being then preſent Mr. Worly had don the meſſage to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:33255:48"/>Gentleman that had the command in the abſence of the other, the ſaid Officer ſhould have anſwered that he much wondred they ſhould make ſuch a work of one or two Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſhot, and pointing with his finger to divers Peeces not far off from him, ſhould have ſaid, behold there a great many, which ſhall be ſhot of, and not fayling of his word, the ſame afternoon 21. Auguſt he made two ſhot more, after the ſame manner as before.</p>
                        <p>That the Mallayans being affrighted, the greater part which remained with the Engliſh, deſerted them.</p>
                        <p>That the Hollanders being advertiſed hereof, embarqued in their Chalops the Mallayans with a number of Dutch Soldiers.</p>
                        <p>That they fired continally their great Guns while they were in their Barqs, and at length having ſet foot on land, they with furie aſſaulted the ſmall number of Mallayans, which were for the Engliſh, ſet on fire their Palliſado, and having put to flight the ſaid Mallayans, they fell upon the Engliſh which were at the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the Palliſado.</p>
                        <p>That a certain man named Mackolon, an Officer of the Hollanders, told him, that except he ſought to eſcape, the Mallayans would kill him.</p>
                        <p>That not fearing their threats, the Holland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders had commanded the Mallayans to aſſault the Engliſh, but the Mallayans teſtifying their
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:33255:49"/>diſlike by refuſing to do it, the Enſign-bearer ſet himſelf in the front, forced an entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Fort, being followed of ſome Mallayans and about 40. Hollanders.</p>
                        <p>That theſe Troopes were no ſooner paſt the Palliſſado, but they ſaid to them and the other Engliſh, that if ever they entred more into the Fort, they might expect nothing elſe, but to be fallen upon.</p>
                        <p>That at the verie ſame inſtant the Dutch Soldiers and the Mallayans began to plunder, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying away all they thought was of any worth, and gave it into the hands of their Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and while they were thus pillaging, the Dutch Soldiers in contempt, brake and tare in pieces the Flag of the King of England, which was ſet up there.</p>
                        <p>That after all theſe Violences the foreſaid Officer by order of the Commander, prayd him to retire on the ſide of the Hollanders, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing in the name of the Commander, they would reſtore the Marchandiſe, Effects, Silver-work, Canon and all what might appertain to the Engliſh, and what ſhould be found in the hands of the Mallayans.</p>
                        <p>That he thereupon going to the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der named Mackabon: he inſtead of performing what was promiſed, anſwered him, he could do nothing in it, and that what the Mallayans had taken, was juſtly acquired, and they could not be conſtrained to render the ſame: however
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:33255:49"/>as for the Canon he would endeavor they might be reſtored.</p>
                        <p>But coming again to him, after he had ordered men and a boat to take in the Canon, there came ſome of his men and ſaid, that in caſe we would have the Canon, the Mallayans pretended to have 500 dollars for them.</p>
                        <p>Seeing then too appearently that in this and in all other things the Engliſh were meerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded, he embarqued his Soldiers and men that were left, and returned to Indrapanna the 25. Auguſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="letter">
                        <opener>
                           <salute>High and Mightie Lords,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>WE have received your Puiſ: Highneſſes Letter and therewith your Reſolution of the firſt of this preſent, with an inſertion of the Memorial preſented to your Puiſſ: Highneſſes, with an annex by the Marquis of Albiville Envoy Extraordinarie of his Royal Majeſtie of Great Brittain, which ſaid Memorial containeth Complaints againſt the tranſactions and doings of the Miniſters of the Netherlandiſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie at Maſlapatnam upon the Coaſt of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandel and at Batancapas upon the Weſt-coaſt of Sumatra, with their Requeſt of reparation, concerning which your Puiſſ: Highneſſes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire information by us. We may not omit, High and Mightie Lords, to propoſe, with all
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:33255:50"/>dutiful reſpect to your Puiſſ. Highneſſes, that foraſmuch as the ſaid Appendix, is in effect the contents of ſuch Letters, which the Engliſh Company, as they pretend, have lately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived out of the Indies, divers particulars are rehearſed in what manner the things they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of were there tranſacted, of which we, by reaſon our Ships are not yet arrived, tho ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected everie houre, cannot have perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, may it therefore pleaſe your Puiſſ: Highneſſes not to conſter it amis, that we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the ſame a while; however we ſay afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, that the ſaid complaints, as they are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the ſaid Memorial, are of two parts.</p>
                        <p>Firſt, againſt the conduct of our people, in their actings at Maſlupatnam: And ſecondly upon the Weſt-Coaſt of Sumatra, with the wrong don to the Engliſh at both places.</p>
                        <p>As to the firſt, we apprehend, that by the information we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>d the laſt year out of India, and by another hand, (ſetting aſide what we are yet exſpecting) we want noe matter fully to juſtifie the tranſactions of our people there, and to demonſtrate the ungroundedneſs of the foreſaid complaints.</p>
                        <p>And what concerns the ſecond, namely that by force we ſhould have hindered them, that they could nor might ſettle themſelves in the Countrie of the Prince of Indraponna, nor build Forts where they pleaſed, whereas that Prince, according to what they affirm, had made over
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:33255:50"/>that Countrie to them, although we can not directly diſcover the perfect ſtate and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that buſineſs, vntil the Ships, which we dayly expect be arrived, nevertheleſs we are able by the information which we had the laſt year concerning it, to affirm from the contents of thoſe Letters, that the Engliſh by reaſon of the unhealthfultneſs of that countrie, and the mortalitie it brought upon their men, with other difficulties, were entended yea did actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally prepare do depart thence, ſo that we thought to have mentioned nothing more, nor troubled your Puiſ: Highneſſes with that buſineſs, but have paſt it by in ſilence, but ſeeing out the foregoing Appendix we find it otherwiſe, we ſhall nor may not neglect to produce with the firſt opportunitie unto your Puiſ: Highneſſ: our juſt complaints, and withal to ſhew the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, loſſes and intruſions of the Engliſh upon the proprietie and right, which we (as to the Weſt-coaſt) for a verie long time have had and acquired, and which we yet have the actual poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion and injoyment of, and can prove that they continually have ſought to debauch, and draw from us theſe Princes, who in acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of the benefits and ſervices they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from us, and among many other, that we had delivered them at our exceediing charge and expences out of the hands of their enemies under whoſe yoke they were brought, and moreover at whoſe Requeſt, we have by ſolemn
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:33255:51"/>Contracts taken upon us, and promiſed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them againſt all and every one who ſhould offer to do any injurie or violence unto them and for which they have declared us for their Sonverains, and in eſpecial alſo that foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Prince of Indraponna, in whoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey they have built a Fort, endeavouring forceablie to thruſt us out of our poſſeſſion, by depriving us of the injoyment we had: And yet they themſelves confeſs that our people on the Weſt-Coaſt have poteſted againſt the injuries they did to them, while they ſought to ſettle themſelves at Boucoulo and Indro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponna, countries and places, as the real truth is, belonging to us, of which the Contracts are in our hands time out of mind, and yet they cannot deny, that their people have ſet themſelves againſt us by building of Forts to keep us out, yea they complain that we by raiſing a Fort have injuried and prevented them, and yet this is all the dammage and wrong, according to their own ſaying we have don them. If indeed the Engliſh could make it out and maintain, that they have a right, to com into a countrie of which the Soveraintie is made over to us, beſide other engagements we have there, tho as they ſay, by conſent of the ſaid Prince (although that is not by us owned as true) to build Forts thereby to draw the Commerce into their hands, with the ſecluding of us, to whom the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:33255:51"/>right is only belonging, and yet we not have juſte cauſe, by raiſing a Fort to prevent them: or that hereby they ſhould have a main action againſt us: certainly this muſt needs come from another law then hitherto hath bin known to the world. They accuſe us that we by <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative</hi> Contracts have ſought everie where to keep them from trading, and yet they make their appeal to ſuch like Contracts, which themſelves have made there. The Engliſh Companie ſhewes that they wilfully continue in their cuſtom to make alwayes complaints how impertinent or ungrounded ſoever, thereby to preoccupy the world, yea to make an impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion even in the inhabitants of this State it ſelf, as if we ſought nothing elſe, but made it our whole buſineſs to oppoſe and be thwarting of the Engliſh, as amongſt other their complaints, this alſo may apparently be ſeen in the buſineſs of Bantam, which occaſioned ſuch commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and klatter almoſt in all places, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which the information ſtated by this Chamber above a year ago, and preſented to your Puiſ: Highneſſes hath clearly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, what is to be judged of the carriage and conduct of the Netherlandiſh Companie in that matter, which in the firſt was ſo odiouſly ſet forth. But forasmuch as it is our intention after the arrival of our Ships, whoſe return from the Indies, we dayly expect, more am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, by the permiſſion of your Puiſſ: Highneſſes
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:33255:52"/>to treat of theſe and other things, when we ſhall have further light by the evidences we expect in thoſe Ships, and to ſhew the injuries offred us; we will herewith conclude, praying, &amp;c.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Beneath ſtood, High and Mighty Lords, <hi>Your moſt humble Servants,</hi> The Directors of the Eaſt-Indie Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of the Chamber of Amſterdam, and from thence, In the Margin,</signed>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>In Amſterdam</hi> 
                              <date>7. <hi>Aug:</hi> 1687.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="text">
                  <head>ERRATA.</head>
                  <p>Pag. 24. lin. 14. after young, ad King.</p>
                  <p>Pag. 82. ſix lines from the end, for <hi>Cope</hi> read <hi>Copie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33255:52"/>
                  <head>To the High and Mighty Lords, The STATES GENERAL of the United Netherlands.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>High and Mighry Lords:</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe Chamber of the <hi>Eaſt-Indie Company</hi> of Amſterdam, hath after the Aſſembling of the <hi>Seventien</hi> repreſenting the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and brought your puiſſant Highneſſes Letter, with the annexed Reſolution, both being of the firſt of Auguſt now paſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining an Inſertion of the <hi>Memorial</hi> of the Marquis of <hi>Albiville,</hi> Envoy Extraordinary of his Royal Majeſty of Great <hi>Brittain,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented unto your Puiſ: Highneſſes, with an Annex; the ſaid <hi>Memorial</hi> containing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints againſt the doing and tranſactions of the Miniſters of our Company at <hi>Maſlupat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,</hi> on the Coaſt of <hi>Cormandel,</hi> and at <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancapas,</hi> upon the Weſt-Coaſt of <hi>Sumatra,</hi> with demand of reparation for the Infractions and dammages, which the Subjects of his ſaid Roya<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Majeſty ſhould have ſuffered at both thoſe places: and concerning which your Puiſſ: Highneſſes were pleaſed to command us to bring in our Information: and by reaſon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33255:53"/>the ſaid Chamber could at that time give only a proviſional Anſwer, dated the 7. of Auguſt, becauſe the Ships by which we expected our Letters of Advice from the <hi>Indies,</hi> concerning theſe Affaires, were not as yet arrived. The laſt whereof, to which we were then neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to refer our ſelves, being by Gods good providence ſome dayes ſince ſafely come unto us, and that thereby we now are in a capacity to inform your Puiſſ: Highneſſes more pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually, we will with permiſſion further ſay, that we find the foreſaid complaints to be two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold: Firſt, over the evil proceeding and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of our men at <hi>Maſlupatnam,</hi> and ſecondly at <hi>Batancapas,</hi> where we, as they ſay, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally have exerciſed injuſtice and violence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
                  <p>What concerns the firſt, it will be neceſſary to dive ſomewhat more groundedly into that buſineſs, viz. After the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> had ſuſtained and born many injuries, dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, and violences by the King of <hi>Golcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> who was miſled by his Chief Miniſters, till at laſt the whole Traffick of the ſaid Company in all the Northern Factories and Lodges was forbidden, and it was commanded to all the Regents and Officers, to deprive all the Factories and Miniſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hereof of all meanes of livelihood, and fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>er that no wever nor handicrafts men ſhould thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward deliver any thing of what they had underhand unto them, all which was direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33255:53"/>contrary to the Octroy and Patents granted unto the ſaid Company. That at laſt we jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it reaſonable to have recourſe to force and conſtraint, hoping thereby if poſſible to bring the King to better and more moderate thoughts, but before we would enter upon it, we though it beſt in an orderly way, to make our intent known to the King, who is judged by all to be a Prince of a good nature, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways hath ſhewn himſelf affectioned to the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlandish Company,</hi> and the rather becauſe the Government of <hi>Batavia,</hi> were fully aſſured that theſe Infractions and Troubles were oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned to our Company only by the evilaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and ill will of <hi>Madolena</hi> and <hi>Achena,</hi> the two Chief <hi>Miniſters</hi> of that Kingdom, who had ſo remarkably injured the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and invented a way to incite their King againſt us, without any right information how the caſe ſtood betwixt him and us, which ſaid <hi>Miniſters</hi> a while after by reaſon of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward commotions occaſioned by their ill ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of Affairs came to a moſt miſerable End. However the ſaid Government of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavia,</hi> to the end aforementioned ſent a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſarie</hi> with full Commiſſion and Power to treat with the King, and if it might be to compoſe all things in a way of amitie: But our <hi>Commiſsary</hi> was ſo unſucceſsful, that the King either could or would not aſſent to what we judged to be right and equal, in ſo much that to acquire the foreſaid reparation and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33255:54"/>ſatisfaction, we were neceſſitated by force of Arms, to aſſure and make our ſelves Maſter of <hi>Maſlupatnam,</hi> in hope thereby to induce the King the ſooner to liſten to an accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation, which alſo the 16. of July 1686. was effected without blood ſhed, and the Kings Militia was cauſed to depart, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon we fortifyed the City againſt any inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which might happen. And becauſe the <hi>English Company</hi> had a <hi>Factory</hi> and a <hi>Lodge</hi> there for their Commerce and Traffick, we by Letters in Auguſt following, let them or their <hi>Miniſters</hi> know, that however we had the Power and poſſeſſion of the City in our hands, our intention was not in the leaſt to hinder or incommodate their Traffick, and that they might conſequentially diſpoſe of, and lade their goods they had or could make ready in their Ships, together with all their Proviſion and Marchandiſes, which might by Sea be brought unto them, and take it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Lodge, only that they ſhould not diſpoſe of them to the Subjects of that King, nor after the expiration of ſix or eight weeks ſuffer any goods more to be brought to them out of the Country.</p>
                  <p>This being thus paſſed, and we perceiving that the Enemy began to ſtirr, and to caſt up works to beſiege us, and gather an Army thereby to deprive us of our water and other means of Livelihood, we ſent out our men againſt them, and with ſucceſs raiſed the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33255:54"/>Kings forces by driving them out of their Tents: and forasmuch as the Enemy had threatned and intended to burn the City, which was all built of Combuſtible matter, thereupon the <hi>English,</hi> with diverſe others of the Inhabitants for fear of being conſumed by fire, retired upward into the Country, but the King ſoon after reſolving to come to a treatie of accomodation with us, which alſo was at length effected, by the promiſing repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Dammages, and that for the future they ſhould no more deal thus unjuſtly with us, but ſuffer us to enjoy free trading as formerly; all which being agreed unto, we withdrew our Militia out the City, and gave it up again into the hands of the King.</p>
                  <p>This being the true ſtate of the matter, hereupon the <hi>English</hi> Company makes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints by an Annex, to which the Memorial of the Marquis of <hi>Albiville</hi> hath relation, over Injuries and Violences offered them at <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlupatnam,</hi> under the pretext of a War, which the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> had under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken againſt the King of <hi>Golconda:</hi> but they ſay they are well acquainted with ſuch Tricks and Deſigns. And that we made our ſelves Maſters of <hi>Maſlupatnam,</hi> after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner we before haddon of <hi>Bantam,</hi> to no other end then thereby to ruinate and deprive the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh of their Traffick.</p>
                  <p>That we had play'd ſuch prancks to often, eſpecially at <hi>Bantam,</hi> and afterward at <hi>Suma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra,</hi>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:33255:55"/>however they doubted not but we ſhould be reſponſable for the ſame.</p>
                  <p>That we forbade them after the Expiration of eight weeks to trade any more at <hi>Maſlu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patnam,</hi> notwithſtanding they there have had their place of Reſidence and Magaſin above eighty or ninety years together, and had built the ſame at their expences upon ground bought with their own money.</p>
                  <p>That in all the Treaties we have made with the Kings and Princes of thoſe Countries, we always endeavoured to exclude their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany from the Trade and Havens of thoſe places, thereby wholy to annihilate their Commerce, but that notwithſtanding the foreſaid Inſinuation they did intend to keep up their trading at <hi>Maſlupatnam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Truly here is a wonderful kind of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and by it may be perceived, how eaſy it is to Miſconſter a ſincere and upright inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and wreſt it to a bad ſenſe.</p>
                  <p>The queſtions then naturally flowing from hence are theſe, viz.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Whether our Company did undertake this War out of an evil intention and deſire, under that pretext to offer injury and violence to the <hi>English.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, Whether it be true, that our Deſign was to make our ſelves Maſters of <hi>Maſlupatnam,</hi> after the ſame manner as we had don of <hi>Bantam,</hi> and with no other end and intention than thereby to effect the ruine
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33255:55"/>of the Commerce of the <hi>English.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Whether it be true, that we had forbode them their Traffick at <hi>Maſlupatnam,</hi> after the expiring of eight weeks.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Whether it then were, or yet is in the power of the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> to enter into ſuch Leagues and Contracts with the Princes of thoſe Countries, by which other Nations ſhould be ſecluded from trading in any of the Wares or Fruits growing in thoſe Countries.</p>
                  <p>What concerns the firſt, it is known to all, that the <hi>Eaſt Indie Company</hi> of theſe Lands, is the only erected Companie of Commerce for to enjoy by and thro an honeſt trading in Countries ſo far remote from us, the profits which we hoped might thence enſue.</p>
                  <p>But forasmuch as we found by ſad expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that we ſhould have to doe with Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which were not to be too much truſted, and had evilly entreated many of our Traders, yea, murdered ſome of them, which before an Octroy was granted, had negotiated with them, it ſeemed good to the <hi>States</hi> of our Country, to prevent ſuch miſchiefs, to qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lify and Authoriſe by a granted Octroy to this <hi>Company,</hi> to procure reparation by all ſuch meanes as ſhould be judged moſt conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient by them, with further Authority to make Leagues and Contracts with the <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Potentates</hi> of thoſe Nations, and to erect and build Forts and Caſtles as might ſerve for their ſecurity.</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:33255:56"/>
                  <p>Theſe Wars then were not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, but only in caſe of urgent neceſſity, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all wayes of Accommodation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention had in vain been attempted.</p>
                  <p>It is a thing that ſpeaks of it ſelf, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Marchandiſing and War there is no a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, and that Merchants can no wiſe have any intereſt thereby, and the <hi>Companie</hi> therefore had preciſe Orders to ſhun it as much as poſſibly might be.</p>
                  <p>So that it is moſt abſurd to ſuppoſe the <hi>Company</hi> ſhould have engaged in that War againſt the King of <hi>Golconda,</hi> ſo potent a Prince, and only out of a jollitie of ſpirit, A War which we knew aforehand, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the ceſſation of Traffick, would draw after it ſuch charges and loſſes, without any expectation (ſave only hopes of reparation and dammages ſuſtained) the verie leaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit imaginable, muchleſs, that our main aim ſhould have been to incommodate the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish,</hi> or eauſe other Dammage to accrue to them. Certainly the ſaid <hi>Netherlandish Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> ought not to be lookt upon ſo void of all ſenſe as to caſt themſelves upon ſuch heavie charges and troubles by a War, the iſſue of which is uncertain, and that only to incommodate and cauſe ſome loſs to a <hi>third partie,</hi> whereas the charges and hinderance to their own Commerce would be of more importance an hundred fold, then the Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of that <hi>third partie</hi> could amount to.</p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:33255:56"/>
                  <p>And beſides what hath the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> further and more inſiſted upon or obtained, then the continuance of their former Commerce, according as it was granted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them by Octroy, or, as they call it in thoſe Countreys, by <hi>Firman?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Have they made any Contracts with the King to the prejudice or dammage of the <hi>English Company?</hi> Not in the leaſt: What a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement or compariſon then is there between this buſineſs and <hi>Bantam?</hi> In <hi>Bantam</hi> the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlandish Company</hi> was Auxiliary to Succour an oppreſſed King, whoſe condition and ſtate was brought to the very point of utter ruine, and who in this deſperate juncture im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plored our Auxiliary Forces againſt his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, and by whoſe means he was delivered from that oppreſſion.</p>
                  <p>For which the King granted, or rather, we bargained and required nothing elſe, but the Trade in his City and Country, with Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of all other, not to continue alwayes, but only ſo long till the promiſe made of reim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourſing the charges we had been at in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording our help to him, and which by mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual conſent was ſummed up, ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
                  <p>This alſo may ſerve to demonſtrate the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the <hi>Netherlandish Companie,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the intereſt of the <hi>English Companie.</hi> True the Troopes of the <hi>Netherlandish Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> are ſtill in <hi>Bantam;</hi> but hath not the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33255:57"/>King power to this? May he not retain them in his City for his ſervice and the ſecurity of his Perſon and State, and without whom he could not, as he declareth, ſubſiſt or be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure among his Subjects, eſpecially thoſe that had been up in Rebellion againſt him, of whom he was not much beloved, and alſo the Old King his Father, being yet alive.</p>
                  <p>By this alſo an Anſwer is ſufficiently made unto the ſecond Point, with this Addition only, that it is very rediculous to think, that the <hi>Dutch Company</hi> ſhould have intended by this War aganſt <hi>Golconda;</hi> to plot the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw and ruin of the <hi>English Companies</hi> Commerce (which notwithſtanding they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiouſly lay to our charge) as by the event alſo hath clearly appeared.</p>
                  <p>And becauſe, as before hath been ſaid, we foreſaw that the Erecting of the <hi>Netherlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dish Company</hi> in the <hi>Indies,</hi> could not be maintained without force of Armes, therefore, as has been ſaid, the <hi>States</hi> did in a ſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner authoriſe them thereto.</p>
                  <p>Whereupon the <hi>English Company</hi> percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving they were deprived of ſuch a power, did in imitation, of what the <hi>States</hi> had granted to us, alſo procure an <hi>Octroy</hi> or <hi>Charter</hi> from the King now reigning, of which till that time they were unprovided, and by reaſon of which, were fain to ſuffer thoſe injuries and Violences patiently, which now the one and then another of the Princes, Potentates, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33255:57"/>Nations moleſted them with, and ſtill muſt have ſuffered, had they not by ſpecial Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity been impowred to an offenſive War in ſuch caſe as might fall out. And therefore as ſoon as they had obtained that Charter, they by virtue thereof took up Arms againſt the <hi>Great Mogol</hi> in <hi>Bengale,</hi> and as is thought alſo in <hi>Suratte.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And might not now the <hi>Dutch Companie</hi> with as good ground and reaſon affirm, that the <hi>English Company</hi> hath undertaken this War, thereby to incommodate, endammage and enterrupt us in our Trading, which is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſiderable in thoſe Countries.</p>
                  <p>And in caſe we ſhould make complaints a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, would they deſiſt, or be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to make no further Progreſs in their Affairs? Undoubtly they would not. Or if we ſhould hereupon become troubleſom to them, might they not juſtly help themſelves with the known Rule, <hi>that he who uſeth his own Right, doth hurt no man thereby.</hi> Yet thus <hi>Self-love</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi> doth blind the Eyes of men.</p>
                  <p>We only wiſh and deſire, that in ſuch caſes of their Warr, which they wage, our <hi>Dutch Company</hi> may be treated, and have the ſame meaſure as the <hi>English Company</hi> hath had, all the while the <hi>Dutch Company</hi> made War with the King of <hi>Perſia</hi> and <hi>Golconda.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The third Point, ſo as it is couched and laid down in the <hi>Annex</hi> of the <hi>Memorial</hi> of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33255:58"/>Marquis of <hi>Albiville,</hi> is altogether abuſive and untrue, to wit, That we had forbidden them after the expiring of eight weekes to negotiate there any more.</p>
                  <p>True, we underſtood it fit, and ſo forbade them that after the expiration of eight weekes, they ſhould bring no more Wares which they might have beſpoken, from the Countrie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the City, for if they would, they had op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities enough to bring in all they had du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this time.</p>
                  <p>But here the queſion may be: Whether in this we have not don amiſs and contrary to <hi>Right of Nations?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, by Sea we hindred them not, but out of our own goodwill, although we had a Squadron of Ships before the City, permitted them freely to traffick; yea they might du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſpace of theſe eight weeks, cauſe all what they had in the Country to be brought unto them. Now in ſtead that they ought to have taken and owned this as a great Civilitie condeſcention and benefit to them, this they make a point or Article of their complaint and accuſation, but with as little ground, as in all the reſt.</p>
                  <p>It is well known, that when the <hi>French, English, Spaniard, Portugiſes</hi> and others, make Conqueſts of any Countries or Places beyond <hi>Europe,</hi> they then forbid Navigation and Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick unto all Strangers in the ſaid placcs.</p>
                  <p>Yea ſo far that ſome of them, if they only
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33255:58"/>ſpie at Sea a ſtrange ſhip though at ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſeemingly approching their Countries, they bord, take and confiſcate them.</p>
                  <p>In conformity and according to this practiſe the <hi>Netherlandish Company,</hi> after they were becom maſters of <hi>Maſlupatnam,</hi> might have forbidden the <hi>Navigation</hi> and all Commerce unto the <hi>English Company.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For altho the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> made uſe and tooke poſſeſſion of the City, to no other End, then only to bring the King of <hi>Golconda</hi> the ſooner to reaſonable termes; yet they could not be certain, whether it ſhould have ſuch ſucceſs as they expected, or how long it might be before it were effected.</p>
                  <p>And in the mean while, why might they not order themſelves according to the <hi>Rule</hi> of other Nations, and eſpecially that which the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish</hi> themſelves beyond <hi>Europe</hi> doe practiſe; yea which the <hi>English Company</hi> doth do in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> alſo, as ſhall more largely by and by be dilated.</p>
                  <p>How then can it be ill taken or imputed an Injurie don by the <hi>Dutch Company,</hi> that they only required, that the <hi>English Company,</hi> after the expiration of eight weekes, ſhould let no more Wares of the Country, to be brought into the City, or to hold correſpondence with the Enemies of the <hi>Netherlandish Company.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For if all what was carried out, and brought in into the City, ſhould have been at the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the <hi>English Company,</hi> while the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33255:59"/>lay poſted with his Army round about the ſame, it would certainly have been of too dangerous a conſequence to the <hi>Netherlandish Company.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They might therefore during the time the City was in their power, in matters of ſuch a nature, order and diſpoſe of things, as they judged moſt convenient.</p>
                  <p>Neither can any juſtly interpret this in an evil ſenſe, although it had been don here in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope:</hi> Namely to forbid that in a City ſurroun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and beſieged by Land, nothing be brought in and out, and that thro the Army of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, who undoubtedly neither could nor would permit the ſame.</p>
                  <p>But put the caſe that it might in ſome reſpect be controverted and diſputed (which certainly in reaſon can not be imagined) yet then it ought to be enquired into, whether by that Letter or Inſinuation any dammage did accrue unto them.</p>
                  <p>For, as before hath been ſaid, the <hi>English</hi> did of their own accord retire out of <hi>Maſlu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patnam,</hi> leaving the City for fear of being burnt by fire.</p>
                  <p>And again, they do not ſay, that any ſtop or hinderance was done to them in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce: for on the contrary in their Anſwer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Inſinuation (as may be ſeen in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Annex to the <hi>Memorial</hi> of the Marquis of <hi>Albiville</hi>) they affirm that they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue their Traffick as before.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:33255:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>Thirdly, the Engliſh had divers other Lodges more, by, or not far from <hi>Maſlupat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,</hi> where they could without any moleſt drive their trade <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yea <hi>Madraſpamen</hi> it ſelf, and the Fort <hi>St. George,</hi> which was their own Place and Fortreſſe, being alſo in the ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Golconda,</hi> and where they have their Capital or chief Houſe of trading, lying alſo neere thereunto.</p>
                  <p>And forasmuch as they could there receive Wares out of that Kingdom as well as out of <hi>Maſlupatnam,</hi> hence it manifeſtly appeareth that the ſuſpition which the <hi>English Company</hi> would blot us with, as if we had remarkablie injured them in their Traffick in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Golconda,</hi> is altogether ungrounded and frivolous.</p>
                  <p>The following fourth Point, concerning the making of Contracts <hi>Privative</hi> (or by way of Secluſion) with divers Princes in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> about ſome kind of Wares and Fruits growing in their Countries, ſhall be ſpoken to hereafter, upon the ſubject treating of the Weſt Coaſt of <hi>Sumatra.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Comming then to the ſecond Capital point, to wit, the Infraction and dammages our men ſhould have done to the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tch</hi> at <hi>Batancapas,</hi> lying on the Weſt-Coaſt of <hi>Sumatra,</hi> we will with the permiſſion of your Puiſſ. Highneſſes, firſt a little ſpeak of the commodiouſneſs and conveniences of thoſe Countries, and then come to the Matter it ſelf.</p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:33255:60"/>
                  <p>It is thus, the foreſaid Coaſt is divided into divers Regions and Juriſdictions, of which <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coulo, Sillebaer,</hi> and from thence to the <hi>South,</hi> far beyond the Straites of <hi>Sunda,</hi> do belong to the King of <hi>Bantam,</hi> and again from <hi>Boncoule Northwards</hi> unto <hi>Sinckal,</hi> are under the Command of the <hi>Netherlandish Company.</hi> The Prince and People of theſe Countries were in part ſubjected to the <hi>Netherlndish Company,</hi> for and in acknowledgment of the Benefits they had received from us, being to our vaſt expences and trouble, freed from oppreſſion, and having our promiſe to take them into our protection.</p>
                  <p>And partly by the War theſe mutinous and unfaithful people waged againſt us, for thereby beeing ſubdued and brought under our power, they were forced not only to acknowledg that Soverainity we had, but alſo by Contract to oblige themſelves to deliver unto us at a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain rate all the Pepper and other commodities their Countries yielded with excluding of all other Nations, not only <hi>Indians,</hi> but <hi>Europians</hi> alſo.</p>
                  <p>And what concerns <hi>Boncoulo,</hi> it is true the <hi>English</hi> ſome years paſt, came with their Forces, and poſſeſſed themſclves thereof, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretext that the Old King of <hi>Bantam</hi> had during the Civil Wars (in which he was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Priſoner) granted to them free Trading, and Habitation at <hi>Sillebaer,</hi> but were driven out of the laſt place by the forces of the King
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33255:60"/>that now reigneth in <hi>Bantam,</hi> they retired to <hi>Boucoulo,</hi> and built a Fortreſſe there, where they yet keep their abode, and from thence did tranſport and wreſt out of our hands a verie conſiderable part of Pepper, we ſay, wreſted, forasmuch as it was by Contract with <hi>Bantam</hi> made over to us, whereby although they have intruded into what belonged to us, to our great detriment; yet we will paſs that by, as not being ignorant that ſuch manner of Contracts and Obligations made with Princes in whoſe Countries, where we have only Lodges or Factories, doe give us no ful right actually to hinder other Nations for to buy and tranſport their Commodities, but muſt leave it to the diſpoſal of him that is Lord and Maſter of thoſe Countries.</p>
                  <p>But that we ſhould be conſtrained to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer other Nations to come and Traffick in the Countries where, beſides ſuch Contracts, we have and exerciſe Superiority, and permit them alſo for the ſecurity of their Commerce to build Forts there, is a thing that none who are of a ſound and ſedate Judgment, would ſo much as imagine; and yet this is the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion that here muſt be agitated.</p>
                  <p>For the <hi>English</hi> as hath been ſaid, did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not content themſelves to ſettle at <hi>Boucoulo,</hi> the Territory of <hi>Bantam,</hi> and build a Fortreſſe there, but did advance even to <hi>Indraporina,</hi> took poſt, and erected a Fort there alſo, and this they did, notwithſtanding the Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33255:61"/>and friendly Informations of the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlandish Company</hi> againſt it, as infringing their right, in a Country in ſubjection for many yeares unto the <hi>Dutch Company,</hi> and where they, beſides the Contracts made with the People, doe exerciſe all Acts of Soverain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and of which they have the Agreements and Contracts, lying by them to ſhew. Now this is it, for which the <hi>Dutch Company</hi> doth judge they have reaſon ſo greatlie to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, of which by and by we ſhall more fully ſpeak.</p>
                  <p>Of the ſame nature is that of <hi>Batancapas,</hi> of which in ſpecial mention is made in the foreſaid <hi>Memorial</hi> and <hi>Annex,</hi> lying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Indraporina</hi> and <hi>Sullida,</hi> neer about three or four Miles from the laſt place men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, properly appertaining to this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, where they of the <hi>English Company</hi> do themſelves pretend, that by or over againſt our Fort aforeſaid, they alſo erected one, but were prevented by us, and over which prevention they make heavie complaints in their ſaid <hi>Annex,</hi> but without any ground at all, as ſhall appear by what followeth.</p>
                  <p>The Hiſtorie, according as things were tranſacted, is this: After that <hi>Sapoele Boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handſlaers,</hi> unto whom <hi>Batancapas</hi> alſo was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing, being a perfidious and mutinous people, had divers times before, and now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain of late lift up themſelves againſt the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> breaking the fidelity
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33255:61"/>they had ſworn, and the Contracts they had made with them; yet the <hi>Dutch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> upon their ſubmiſſion, and laying down their <hi>Arms</hi> in March 1686. did again receive them into favour, making a ſtrickter Contract with them, and that for the future they would, according to promiſe, remain in their fidelity, Obedience and Submiſſion to the <hi>Netherlandish Company,</hi> and hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward reſpect and obey the Governour at <hi>Badang,</hi> being the chief place of the ſaid Company on the ſaid Weſt-coaſt, without ever declining, upon pain of being declared Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and brought under the everlaſting wrath of God over them and their poſterity; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides with this condition, that all the Gold, Pepper and other Wares their Countries yielded, or which were brought thither, ſhould only be and remain for the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landish Company,</hi> they paying the ordinary price for them, as by the foreſaid Contract in the keeping of the <hi>Dutch Company</hi> is more at large to be ſeen, which was agreed on 15. March 1686. being many Months before the <hi>English Company,</hi> according their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, came to <hi>Batancapas.</hi> And no ſooner were they come thither but endeavoured to miſlead the people of <hi>Batancapas,</hi> and to draw them from their Fidelity and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; but wel knowing what kind of People they were and how little to be truſted, they erected a Fortreſſe in their Land, but
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33255:62"/>were by the <hi>Netherlandish Company,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their own ſaying, prevented by build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Fort there alſo.</p>
                  <p>While things were in this ſtate, it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened that ſome of the Nadias that were fallen of with their men, did in the preſence of ſix Engliſh, as Enemies, ſet upon us in the foreſaid Poſt, and drive our men a Canon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot out of the Fort among the Inhabitants, by which, as was reported, four of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Inlanders were ſlain: but as in ſuch times and caſes of that nature, all are not alike mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinous and of the ſame mind, thereupon they who remained faithful, went out againſt them that were fallen off, to drive them from thence, and made themſelves Maſters of the Engliſh Fort, and except it had been for our intervention, they would have murthered all the Engliſh in their retrait: but whatever they left behind, as they deſired by their Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, was as much as poſſibly could be, not only reſtored to them, but what is more, at their Requeſt we provided them all manner of proviſions of meat and drinck, &amp;c. for which alſo in their Letters dated the 22. and 26. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt 1686. they were very thankful unto us, as we can ſhew by them, in the laſt of which Letters one of their men wrote, that he was come there, to wit to <hi>Batancapas,</hi> with or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſee whether <hi>(Note this well)</hi> he could have the Canon pieces, which the <hi>Malayers</hi> in the Aſſault had found in the Fort, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33255:62"/>to him; but ſeeing that they demanded too much money for them, he would go back to <hi>Indraponra,</hi> and make report thereof to the Commander in Chief: In which it is worthy of obſervation, that in the foreſaid <hi>Annex,</hi> belonging to the forementioned <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial</hi> of the Marquis of <hi>Albiville,</hi> they ſay, that the ſame day they came to <hi>Bantam,</hi> our <hi>Miniſters</hi> ſent them a <hi>Proteſt,</hi> and withall counſelled them to beware of the Malayers, with a Complaint (theſe are their own words) of the Injurie the Engliſh did to us, namely, in that they came to ſettle themſelves at <hi>Batancapas,</hi> and at <hi>Indraponra</hi> alſo, places both appertaining to the <hi>Dutch Company,</hi> and that two dayes after our men had ſent ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Proteſt.</p>
                  <p>The caſe then ſtanding thus actually as is ſaid, the queſtion will be, from which of the two Companies, the <hi>English</hi> or the <hi>Dutch,</hi> the Action doth ariſe, and which of the two hath cauſe to complaine?</p>
                  <p>In caſe the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their expectation, received in their Ships, that laſt arrived out of the <hi>Eaſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> all the particulars and Informations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to this matter, they would not have fayled to make their juſt complaints to your Puiſſ: Highneſſes in a Methodical way; but forasmuch as the Letters of the Government of <hi>Batavia</hi> ſpecifie, that they muſt firſt wait for the Arriral of their Ships from the Weſt-Coaſt,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33255:63"/>the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the ſame, to a fitter opportunity.</p>
                  <p>However by what is already ſaid, it doth ſufficiently appear by what force, violence and intruſion thoſe of the Engliſh Company have acted againſt us, both at <hi>Indraponra,</hi> as alſo at <hi>Batancapas</hi> and elſewhere, and that conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, we have abundant reaſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire reparation and Satisfaction of them.</p>
                  <p>That which the Engliſh Company alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth againſt this, ſo as it is contained in their Annex to the foreſaid <hi>Memorial</hi> of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis of <hi>Albeville,</hi> conſiſts in this.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, the Emperour of <hi>Maniarbohaer</hi> ſhould have conferred and ſetled that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey upon them, and had to this End ſent up two of his Sons to eſtabliſh the Engliſh there.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, that they by vertue thereof ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving built a Fort there, we in a time of peace had by violence aſſaulted them, and this only for the ſecuring of our Traffick in Pepper.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, That we had diſdainfully tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled upon and torn the Pavillion of the King of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, That out of the Fort we had ſhot at the Inhabitants of <hi>Batancapas,</hi> and at them that brought their Wares to Market.</p>
                  <p>And laſtly, that our men had rob'd and taken away all the Marchandiſes, Effects,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33255:63"/>Silverwork, Canon, and whatever they had there.</p>
                  <p>What concerns the firſt point, it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> for many yeares hath had and ſtill hath the Dominion in and over the Countreys where <hi>Batancapas</hi> is ſeated.</p>
                  <p>That this Authoritie and Dominion is now again lately in March 1686. conferred upon them with moſt advantagious conditions, and are thereby ſetled in the peaceable enjoyment thereof: So that they had not any lawful Right to inſtal and deliver up that Countrie into the hands of the Engliſh.</p>
                  <p>For as to the forementioned Emperor, whom the Engliſh ſtile the Emperour of <hi>Manicabo,</hi> it is true that up or in the midſt of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of <hi>Sumatra,</hi> which are Lands of <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabo,</hi> a certain Prince or Emperour doth reign.</p>
                  <p>But that the Prince ever came into the lower part of this Country, and as they pretend, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed the Engliſh there, ſhall while the world ſtands, never be proved by them.</p>
                  <p>For it is certain, that that Emperour never hath been in thoſe lower Countries, alſo in former times thoſe Lower Countries were ſubjected to the uſurped Authority of that Queen <hi>Seehini,</hi> whoſe yoak long agoe they have caſt off, and given over themſelves unto the Dominion of the <hi>Dutch Company,</hi> who have taken upon them to protect and defend them
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33255:64"/>againſt all Oppoſers whatſoever.</p>
                  <p>However, according to our late Letters, it is true that there appeared in theſe Lower Countries two young Lords, ſtiling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Princes, who alſo by ſome were acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged for ſuch, but cryed down and rejected by others as Counterfits.</p>
                  <p>But ſuppoſe they had been true and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Princes, yea the very Sons of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, which can never be proved, yet what right and Authority could they have to eſtabliſh the Engliſh there, muchleſs to make over the Country unto them, or what appearance of Truth can be imagined, they ſhould have don the ſame?</p>
                  <p>It is certain never any of the <hi>English Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> have been up in thoſe Highlands with the Emperour; no not any of Netherlandiſh Company themſelves, notwithſtanding they have lived more then fortie yeares upon the Nether-Coaſt.</p>
                  <p>That thoſe Princes ſhould have Order and Power from their Father to do this, is not ſo much as affirmed, muchleſs proved by the Engliſh Company it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>And although it could be proved, yet it muſt come under examination, whether that Power and Authority could be ſtretched ſo far or not.</p>
                  <p>Yea be it how it will, it is enough for the <hi>Netherlandish Company,</hi> that we according to the confeſſion of the Engliſh themſelves,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33255:64"/>not only were there before them, but alſo that three dayes before their arrival, we had fortifyed our ſelves, yea as they ſay, upon a Rock.</p>
                  <p>Add to this, and which indeed is wholie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciding in the ſubject caſe, that in the very Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Engliſh produce and annexed to the <hi>Memorial</hi> of the Marquis of <hi>Albiville,</hi> and to which he refers himſelf, it is ſaid, that thoſe ſo named Princes did declare, that in caſe the Hollanders ſhould eſtabliſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at <hi>Batancapas</hi> before the Engliſh, that then the Engliſh ſhould be fruſtrated there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Words verie remarkable from ſuch, by whom the Engliſh pretend to have obtained their right, eſpetially it being ſo fallen out as they ſaid.</p>
                  <p>If notwithſtanding the Emperor of <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabo</hi> might pretend any right to thoſe Lands, and declare that we did keep them in our poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion unlawfully, which we ſuppoſe ſhall never be; yet then it would be a queſtion to be decided betwixt the Emperor and us, and not with the Engliſh.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond point is alſo without any ground of truth, to wit, that our men ſhould have taken that Fort by violence from them, the <hi>English</hi> themſelves affirm in a certain Letter, annexed to the foreſaid <hi>Memorial,</hi> that our men did diverſe times incite the <hi>Malbayers,</hi> and urged them to fall upon the <hi>English.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Moreover that one <hi>Mechelen,</hi> whom in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33255:65"/>their foreſaid Annex they name <hi>Muchalon,</hi> Commander in Chief of our Men there ſhould have ſaid to the <hi>English,</hi> and warned them to ſave themſelves, otherwiſe the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leyers</hi> would fall upon and kill them.</p>
                  <p>But that the Engliſh not regarding thoſe threats, at the laſt our men ſhould have commanded the <hi>Maleyers</hi> to fall upon them indeed.</p>
                  <p>Of which if they ſhould be required, to bring in their proof it would be far to ſeek, but on the contrary, it is a certain evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that our men did endeavour their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</p>
                  <p>Hoewever we deny not, that our <hi>Maleyers,</hi> that is, ſuch of them as remained on our ſide, fell upon the other, which rebelled againſt us, and took in the Fort they yet held in their poſſeſſion.</p>
                  <p>It is worthy of Obſervation that the Engliſh themſelves confefs, that not ſo much as a man of them was kild in that action, becauſe we prevented our <hi>Maleyers,</hi> with all our might hindring them from doing it; but ſuppoſe it to be true, tho it be not ſo, that our own men had taken the fort from the Engliſh, what can be juſtly ſaid againſt it? might we not drive them out of a Fort, which in diſpite of us they erected in a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey that belonged to us? and that right over againſt the Fortreſſe we had made there before, and after that by two Proteſts we had warned
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33255:65"/>them not to do it, but would not at all liſten to us.</p>
                  <p>So that as inſtead that the Engliſh take this up a matter of Complaint and accuſation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Netherlandish Company,</hi> they ought to have been thankful to them for their kind and mild dealing with them; yea ſo far as to deliver them from eminent danger of death and ruin.</p>
                  <p>As one <hi>Samuel Bats,</hi> who at that time commanded the Engliſh, together with <hi>John Becton</hi> in their Letters have truely acknowledged.</p>
                  <p>And in caſe one of our Soldiers did, as they affirm in diſdaing tear in peeces the <hi>Pavillion</hi> of the King of England, altho it is not true, for according to the Letters thence received, the Engliſh themſelved pulled down their Flag, which ſurely is more likely to be true, becauſe they apprehending the great danger they were in, would not let the Flag come into hands of their Enemies. But ſuppoſe it were don by an Engliſh Souldier, what blame can be imputed to the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> in this?</p>
                  <p>Why did the Engliſh expoſe the Flag of their King in ſuch manner, in the Territory and Country appertaining to another? Is it not a thing known, that a ſtrange Flag is not reſpected in any place whatſoever?</p>
                  <p>That our men, according to the contents of the fourth point, ſhould have ſhot out of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33255:66"/>Fort with their Canon, is true: But it was don, not before, but after that the <hi>Rebellious Maleyers</hi> had aſſaulted us as Enemies.</p>
                  <p>And put the caſe they had not done it, yet are we not for this reſponſable to the <hi>English Company.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Was it not free for our men to deal with them that had revolted and became Rebels, as they thought meet? Surely if we had dealt more rigourouſly and in an hoſtile manner with them, they had ſufficiently deſerved the ſame.</p>
                  <p>The ſpoiling of their goods they make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of in the fourth point, the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> denyes to have been done by their men. If it was don by the <hi>Maleyers,</hi> as in ſuch occaſions is ordinary, and therefore our State is not reſponſable for that, beſides what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we had preſerved of theirs, was reſtored unto them again, as apperars by the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Letter, in which the Engliſh com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, not that our men had taken their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, but acknowledge it was don by the <hi>Maleyers,</hi> and that it was yet in their poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
                  <p>If then the <hi>Maleyers</hi> could take and carrie away the Canon, how much eaſier was it for them to carrie away other things? So that hereby is a clear and unanſwerable proof, that our people did not intermeddle with that bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, muchleſs that they ſhould be guilty of the ſpoile made.</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:33255:66"/>
                  <p>And beſides all this, the foreſaid <hi>Bats</hi> in the forementioned Letters only deſireth, that we would endeavour to get into our hands, and ſend him his Books and Writings, as alſo two men that were run away with one Moor, together what proviſion of meat and drink they had left, without in the leaſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning any other thing, as well knowing it was not remaining in our, but in the hands of <hi>Maleyers:</hi> neither is it to be imagined to have been of any great importance, for in ſuch a place, where the inevitable danger was fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen dayly by them, and where they had their Chalops and Boats, lying neer their very wals to put in whatſoever was of any worth, it is not eaſily to be believed, they left any thing behind them, they made any great eſteem of, but only what they willingly would part with: and alſo whatever the <hi>Dutch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> could ſave, or get out of the hands of he <hi>Maleyers,</hi> was reſtored unto them.</p>
                  <p>And can theſe men be heard, or any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief given to what was robd and taken from them was delivered into the hands of the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Chief of the <hi>Dutch Company,</hi> as they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatively depoſe in the Anaex of the <hi>Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial</hi> of the Marquis of <hi>Albiville,</hi> whereas in the <hi>Indies</hi> they not only mentioned not a word thereof, but on the contrary by their Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters they declared their thanckfulneſs to that Commander in Chief, for the great Love
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33255:67"/>and Friendſhip he had ſhewed him.</p>
                  <p>Add to this, that when the foreſaid <hi>Bats</hi> worte, that he had received the goods, he ſent for in his foregoing Letters, that if there had been any thing more in our hands, would he not have deſired that it might alſo had have bin conveyed to him? undoubtedly he would.</p>
                  <p>And yet they are not aſhamed to alledge ſuch frivolous things and fictions, if ſo be they might but by any meanes make our caſe odious to the world.</p>
                  <p>For it ſeemeth the <hi>English Company</hi> ſeekes to make it their Cuſtom, by Complaints how ungrounded and futil ſoever they are to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>occupie, and thereby to get an advantage to the prejudice of the <hi>Dutch Companie:</hi> but we doubt but they ſhal fall ſhort of their aim as in this, as they have in the buſineſs of <hi>Bantam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is that which the <hi>English Company</hi> in the <hi>Memorial</hi> they delivered up do make the ground of their Complaints, affirming that the deſign of the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> was nothing elſe then by injuſtice, violence and oppreſſion to ingroſs into their hands the whole Commerce in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> and that, as they add, by continuance. But that they hope His Majeſty of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> will time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provide ſuch remedies whereby ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Intruſions, Invaſions and ingroſſings of the <hi>Netherlandish Companie</hi> may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented.</p>
                  <p>But we would willingly know of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33255:67"/>Company</hi> whence they gather and can make good ſuch Inferences, that they of the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> have ever endeavoured the ſame: Except they have recourſe to ſuch like concluſions, as they have already pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, the ungroundedneſs whereof, we have nakedly and clearly demonſtrated.</p>
                  <p>Beſides it is well known that the Countries in the <hi>Indies</hi> and in <hi>Africa</hi> are ſo great and numerous, the diſtricts almoſt infinite, that it would be a great preſumption, yea folly once to imagin it, not to ſpeak of the abſolute impoſſibility to effect the ſame.</p>
                  <p>'Tis true (and herewith alſo ſhall be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in Anſwer to the fourth point, which we reſerved to this place) that the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> hath with a few unconſiderable Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates or Princes made Contracts over a Privative or Secluſive Traffick of ſome kind Wares which their Countries did yield. But if the <hi>English Company</hi> ſhould maintain this to be an unlawful thing, they muſt condemn their own doing, and ſo as it were pronounce Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt what themſelves have done in former times; and of which many examples may be alledged: Now if the <hi>English Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> hath made ſuch contracts, ſometimes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and ſometimes together with us, when we were in a nearer League Anno 1619. and ſome years following, as may be ſeen and will appear in the <hi>Publick Teſtimonies Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings</hi> lying by us.</p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:33255:68"/>
                  <p>And when the <hi>English Company</hi> had ſuch Contracts with us together, then according to their ſentiment, it was lawful and good. But now the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> doth the ſame without them, as having no communion or fellowſhip in the leaſt with them in the <hi>Indies,</hi> it is condemned and exclaimed againſt by them, as being unreaſonable: Ought they not to call to memorie, that in former times the Engliſh Marchants had the whole Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick of the <hi>Caveyaer</hi> which <hi>Ruſland</hi> or <hi>Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via</hi> did yield.</p>
                  <p>And to come yet cloſer to them, have they not made in the <hi>Indies,</hi> and yet dayly ſeek to make ſuch Contracts, eſpecially on the Coaſt of <hi>Malabaer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> hath ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted here and there ſome Forts for the ſecurity of their Trade, and alſo to make the People of thoſe Countries to ſtand to the Contracts made with them, cannot be imputed a Crime to the <hi>Netherlandish Company,</hi> or the <hi>English Company</hi> muſt confeſs themſelves guiltie of the ſaid crime, for they alſo have made Forts for the ſame end at <hi>Boucoulo</hi> and <hi>Indraponra,</hi> and moreover endeavoured to do the like at <hi>Batancapas,</hi> with what face then can the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Company</hi> blame us in this? and lay it as a grat evil to our charge, whereas they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at <hi>Priaman</hi> (being on the Weſt-Coaſt of <hi>Sumatra,</hi> a Country under the ſubjection
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33255:68"/>of the <hi>Netherlandish Company,</hi> and where they had a Fortreſſe) not only intended, but even actually took in hand to ſettle themſelves, yea alſo according to the Octroy or Charter granted them by the King now reigning, as to other things, ſo in ſpecial to build a Royal Fortreſs, fortifyed with 40 great Peeces of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, Magaſins, Wharfs for Shipping, and all other Houſes and Buildings, there to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect a <hi>Court of Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Admiralty,</hi> and henceforward there to regulate and govern themſelves after the ſame manner, that the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> (theſe are their verie terms) are wont to do in their places, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding them that in the Building of that great and Royal Fort, they ſhould well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the ſecurity of their men, not only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the mutinous People of <hi>Sumatra,</hi> but alſo (which is not to be paſſed by without a Nota bene) againſt their outlandiſh Enemies, the <hi>Hollanders.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For however that deſign of theirs was not effected, becauſe the Engliſh coming there with their Ships, found that the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> themſelves had a Fort there, ſo that had they gon forward, they ſaw it muſt be by falling upon us in a hoſtile way, and drive us from thence, which in appearance they dared not, yet to attempt: may we not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon juſtly demand, whether if they of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Company</hi> having attained to their deſired intent, as to that City would not have kept
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33255:69"/>it alone to themſelves, and whether they would have ſuffered us to trade together with them there? For then the Fortreſs built at ſuch exceſſive charges in that City would have been of no uſe or benefit, but a burthen only.</p>
                  <p>But in caſe they now had near <hi>Priaman</hi> by force of Arms compelled ſome of thoſe Princes thereabout, or that any of them had of their own free will ſubmitted to the <hi>Engliſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,</hi> (for there are diverſe Princes and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, who have every one apart their Juriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Command, and for many years ſince ſubmitted themſelves to us) if I ſay, they ſhould by force of Armes overcom any of the ſaid Princes, or if any of them ſhould willingly, and of their own accord ſubmit to the ſaid <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Company,</hi> and make privative or ſecluſive Contracts with them, tho perhaps they had not built any Forts in the Countrie, and that the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> would thereupon intrude themſelves, and deprive the Engliſh of their intreſt, by building a Fortreſſe, to hinder them from enjoying the Fruits and Benefits of the Contracts made with thoſe Nations: might not in ſuch a caſe the Engliſh juſtly have oppoſed us, yea driven us away by force? un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtly they mought.</p>
                  <p>If then it deſerve to be judged injuſtice, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and oppreſſion in us, by lawful means to ſeek in one and the other Countrie out of or beyond <hi>Europe,</hi> to get and appropriate to our ſelves the Trade thereof: Then we know
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33255:69"/>not, how poſſibly the Engliſh can be judged blameleſs, conſidering what they have don in <hi>Carolina, Virginia, New-England, Jamaica,</hi> and elſewhere, Countries of that vaſt extent, that all what the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> doth poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs in <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> is not to be compared thereunto.</p>
                  <p>And in caſe it be lawful to be don there, why then may it not be don by the <hi>Dutch Company</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies?</hi> except that it can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated, that the Rights of the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> and the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> are not of the ſame nature.</p>
                  <p>But to remain only within the bounds of the <hi>Eaſt-Indies.</hi> The <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> would fain know, upon what account <hi>Sillebaer, Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coulo, Indraponra, &amp;c.</hi> were taken and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by the Engliſh? to what end they erected Forts there? eſpecialy if their deſign at <hi>Pria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> had ſucceeded, was it not to draw and appropriate unto them the Commerce of Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, as much as they could? They endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to make and fortifie <hi>Priaman</hi> in ſuch a manner, for ſo their Orders runs, that they might be in a poſture to withſtand the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> whom they term, their Enemies.</p>
                  <p>If then the <hi>Netherlandish Company,</hi> be thus lookt upon by them, it is no wonder, their Miniſters and Servants in the <hi>Indies</hi> labour to do us all the ſpite, miſchief and injury they poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly can.</p>
                  <p>Whereas on the contrarie our men, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Letters which from time to time
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33255:70"/>we receive thence, endeavour nothing more, then to pleaſe and condeſcend to them in all things, according to the order which our States do continually give unto us: hereby al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, were it poſſible, to free your Puiſſ: High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes from further Complaints and Moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, with which your Puiſſ: Highneſſes are ſo often diſturbed by the Engliſh: but the greater condeſcention we have uſed and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored to ſhew unto them, what advantages and quiet ſoever we endeavoured to procure, what affronts ſoever we paſt by, all is but labor loſt, and the ſucceſſive Letters we receive from the <hi>Indies</hi> teſtifie, is as Oyl caſt into the fire, and only makes them the more audacious and fierce aganſt us.</p>
                  <p>And had we at the firſt at <hi>Indraponra,</hi> ſtoutly oppoſed and hindred them from ſettling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves there, to which we had an indiſputable Right, they would not have ventured to have undertaken, what they did at <hi>Batancapas,</hi> and the troubles thereon enſuing would have been prevented, our condeſcention and indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence being the only occaſion they abuſed thereunto.</p>
                  <p>If at any time infraction or injuſtice hath bin committed, they muſt have recourſe to what happened in the buſineſs on the Weſt-Coaſt, of which the <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> hopes after ſome time to make full diſcoverie to your Puiſſ: Highneſſes.</p>
                  <p>However this is underniable that our Men
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33255:70"/>now lately at <hi>Bengale</hi> did the Engliſh a ſignal ſervice, for when they were in a great extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the Moors had deprived them of all meanes of Livelyhood, then by our mediation and intervention the buſineſs was brought to a ceſſation of all acts of hoſtility for a time: ſo far was it from our intent to plot, or cauſe any harm to come to them, for if it had bin ſo, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fairer opportunity was put into the hands of any, then in that buſineſs of <hi>Bengale,</hi> wherein the Engliſh, beſides the loſs of Hundreds of their men, would have ſuſtained irreparable dammage in their Eſtates and occaſions.</p>
                  <p>At <hi>Batavia</hi> we took them into us, without in the leaſt being obliged thereto, there we harbored them a long time, we permitted their Ships coming in and going out, to enjoy all manner of neceſſaries and refreſhments, notwithſtanding all the continual naſtineſſes and pilfrings of their men; yea thoſe very Ships which came from the Weſt-Coaſt in that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable and deſolate condition, and where they had dealt ſo inhumanely with our men, as hath bin related, yet we provided them not onely with whatever they needed, but alſo let them them repair, and new build them again upon our Wharfs.</p>
                  <p>In caſe the Subjects of our Stase ſhould com to requeſt ſuch a thing of them in the <hi>Caribes, Barbados, Virgina, Jamaica,</hi> or other places, they not only would not have admitted, but rather ſeaſed and confiſcated them. The ſame
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33255:71"/>uſage alſo in likelihood, we might expect from them at <hi>Madraſpatnam,</hi> or their Fort S. <hi>Georg,</hi> where as hath be ſaid, they have ſetled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves on the Coaſt of <hi>Cormandel,</hi> or at leaſt would ſend us packing away from thence.</p>
                  <p>Their Ship the Royal <hi>James</hi> coming in Sept. 1686. from <hi>England,</hi> and arriving at <hi>Priaman,</hi> with the loſs of about 40. Mariners and 30. Soldiers, together with all their Chief Officers unto the verie laſt Sergeant they had, in expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation to have found there a Royal Factorie, but in ſtead thereof meeting with our Men, and departing from thence, at their earneſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, we furniſhed them with all manner of refreſhments, they pleading that becauſe the ſeaſon was wel paſt they entended to ſail to <hi>Padang</hi> in <hi>Bengale,</hi> but in ſtead thereof, they ſtiered their cours to <hi>Indraponra,</hi> where they knew there was nothing to be found for them, ſave men, ammonition and ſuch like neceſſaries for War, with which they provided themſelves the better to maintain the place againſt us.</p>
                  <p>Their Ship the <hi>Herbert,</hi> beeing arrived before <hi>Batavia,</hi> ſome of their men came into the Citie with Pocket Piſtols, and pickt a quarrel in their Lodging in the night, and making uſe of their Piſtols, they were by the aſſiſtance of the People and Magiſtrates Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants diſarmed, their Piſtols by force taken away, otherwiſe it had undoubtedly coſt much Blood, and ſo theſe impudent men were chaſed out of the Citie.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:33255:71"/>
                  <p>And beſides ſome other Ships, the 1. of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember of the laſt yea, there arrived at <hi>Cochin,</hi> a Citie belonging to the <hi>Netherlandish Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> on the Coaſt of <hi>Mallabaer,</hi> a certain En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Fregat (named <hi>Madras,</hi> and the Captain <hi>John Wallis,</hi> comming from <hi>Cormandel,</hi> being bound for <hi>Suratta,</hi> who after he got freſh Victuals and Water, and was without being taken notice of, come abord, he entrepriſed in the night time with a boat propt with men to enter a certain Moors Ship, who ſom dayes before as come from <hi>Suratta</hi> into that <hi>Rode,</hi> he throughly ſearched the ſame, while that 15. Muſquetiers with their Cocks bent lay in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs near unto them, and required the <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del</hi> or Boatſman (the Maſter then being on Land at <hi>Coehin</hi>) to ſhew him his Paſport, who affirming that he had it not, took him along with him out of his Ship, and having brought him a bord his own, with much threatning commanded him to fetch his Pas from Land, but when the ſaid Boatſman was returned from Land, he ſaw that the foreſaid Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was departed, after he thus uſed vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in the Rode, where all ought to be in the greateſt ſecuritie.</p>
                  <p>Again, on the fourth of the ſaid moneth there arrived at <hi>Cochin</hi> for the ſame end an Engliſh Schip called <hi>Carolus Secundus,</hi> mounted with 60 Guns and about threehundred men, <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> and <hi>Soldiers,</hi> having near 50 dead and 80 ſick perſons after he was come from England
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33255:72"/>the foregoing May: and notwithſtanding it was remonſtrated, and complaints made to the Captain <hi>Jonathan Andrews</hi> of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurie and violence he did to our Companie, yet he was not aſhamed to pretend a right to viſit a Moors Ship in our Rode, come hither from <hi>Suratta,</hi> upon the pretext that in the ſaid Moors Ship there were Engliſh Fugitives, however he was at laſt perſwaded to deſiſt.</p>
                  <p>Now in caſe one or more Ships of the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlandish Company</hi> ſhould undertake in the Rhode of <hi>Madraſpatnam,</hi> a Citie as hath bin ſaid, belonging to the Engliſh <hi>Eaſt-Indies Company,</hi> to viſit, ſearch and deal with them after the ſame manner the Engliſh have done in our Rodes, what horrid Exclamations would they not make throughout Europe about it? What pretences of injuries, affronts and dammages would they not divulge? And yet this is the verie thing they dare to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe in our Rodes and Rivers.</p>
                  <p>They complain of Infraction, Wrong, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice offred them: But if ever any wrong or injuſtice hath been done, it is apparently to be ſeen in this, and in a matter of ſuch tenderneſs and conſequence.</p>
                  <p>We paſſe by in ſilence, that the Engliſh have endeavoured, and yet continue dayly to debauch and intice our men by money to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert us and enter into their ſervice, witneſſe what they do at <hi>Bengale,</hi> upon the Coaſt of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandel, Suratta,</hi> and elſewhere, neither have
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33255:72"/>we ever been able to make them to deſiſt from theſe their continued practiſes for ſo many years ſucceſſively, by all the Proteſtations and Complaints made and delivered up unto them: And in caſe we feared not to be overtrouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom to your Puiſſ. Highneſſes in the rehearſal of many other matters and tranſactions, whereby the greateſt wrong and injuſtice ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable hath been offred us: The <hi>Netherlandish Company</hi> could more amply enlarge and extend theſe things. But with the permiſſion of your Puiſſ: Highneſſes we ſhall reſerve the ſame to another opportunity.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>P. VAN DAM.</signed>
                     <dateline>Delivered <date>the 4. Octob. 1687.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
